<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Persecution appearing with its own open face, in William Armorer as will be sufficiently manifest to all that may impartially read this following relation of the cruel proceedings of the said William Armorer, with some others, against the innocent people of GOd called Quackers, in the town of Reading, in the county of Berks, of his taking them up, and imprisoning great numbers of them, and of the continuance of their sufferings to this day, being almost three years and a half : and of his unwearied and cruel practices against that innocent people from time to time : discovered and laid open, to the end that lyes and false reports may be stopped and that the King and all people may be rightly informed, and truly acquainted with the case, as it is clearly and truly in it self.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12485</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12202377</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12202377</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56124</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56124)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 615:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Persecution appearing with its own open face, in William Armorer as will be sufficiently manifest to all that may impartially read this following relation of the cruel proceedings of the said William Armorer, with some others, against the innocent people of GOd called Quackers, in the town of Reading, in the county of Berks, of his taking them up, and imprisoning great numbers of them, and of the continuance of their sufferings to this day, being almost three years and a half : and of his unwearied and cruel practices against that innocent people from time to time : discovered and laid open, to the end that lyes and false reports may be stopped and that the King and all people may be rightly informed, and truly acquainted with the case, as it is clearly and truly in it self.</title>
                  <author>Armorer, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page numbers added by hand: 821-911.</note>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: From the prisoners called Quakers, in Reading-gaol, the 13th day of the 6th month, 1667.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Reading.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56124:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56124:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Perſecution APPEARING With its own OPEN FACE, IN <hi>WILIAM ARMORER:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As will be ſufficiently manifeſt to all that may impartially read this following Relation of the Cruel Proceedings of the ſaid <hi>William Armorer,</hi> with ſome others, againſt the Innocent People of God called QUAKERS, in the Town of <hi>Reading,</hi> in the County of <hi>Berks:</hi> Of his taking of them up, and Impriſoning great Numbers of them: And of the eontinuance of their Sufferings to this day, being almoſt Three years and a half. And of his unwearied and Cruel Practices againſt that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent People from time to time.</p>
            <p>Diſcovered and laid open, to the end that Lyes and falſe Reports may be ſtopped, and that the King and all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may be rightly informed, and truly acquainted with the Caſe, as it is clearly and truly in it ſelf.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matt. 5. 11, 12.</bibl> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my ſake; rejoice and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven; for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were before you.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rev. 2. 10.</bibl> 
               <hi>Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer; behold, the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 119. 126.</bibl> 
               <hi>It is time for thee, Lord, to work, for they have made void thy Law.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56124:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56124:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou mayeſt be ſenſible, That great and many have been the Trials and Sufferings of the People of God in Ages and Generations paſt, who did bear witneſs againſt wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kdeneſs, Idolatry and Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all the unrighteous Laws and Decrees of men; bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a righteous Teſtimony for God, his Way and Truth, upon earth; for which cauſe they have always been perſecuted by wicked and ungodly men, whom the Devil, the Enemy of mankind, hath always made his Inſtruments, to withſtand the work of the Lord God in every diſpenſation of time, wherein the Lord hath been pleaſed to appear and manifeſt himſelf unto men; and as Truth and Righteouſneſs hath flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and born rule in the heart, and the true worſhipped of God been exalted and ſet up; ſo much the more hath Deceit, Cruelty and Oppreſſion, appeared againſt it, through wicked and cruel-minded men; whereby the Lord was diſpleaſed and provoked to anger, and his indignation and wrath was many times kindled againſt the Kings and Rulers of the Earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Afflictions and Oppreſſions of his People, which he did ſee and take great notice of; as the heavy Plagues, and dreadful Judgments which were known and felt in the earth, were ſignal Teſtimonies of; whereby (for the Cauſe before-mentioned) they were brought to perpetual ſhame and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and an example to all that ſhould come after, and tread in their foot-ſteps. As in the caſe of <hi>Cain,</hi> who was wrath, and ſlew his brother <hi>Abel</hi> about Sacrifice, becauſe <hi>Abel</hi>'s was
<pb facs="tcp:56124:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> accepted, and his was not, being wicked; and <hi>Abel</hi> off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red unto God a more acceptable Sacrifice then <hi>Cain;</hi> by which he obtained witneſs that he was righteous, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. Alſo in the caſe of <hi>Lot,</hi> it may be ſeen how wickedneſs and oppreſſion did abound in the men of <hi>Sodom</hi> against him; and how they compaſſed his houſe, becauſe of the men, the Angels of the Lord, which were with him; and preſſed to break the door, to ſearch for the ſtrangers: Theſe were the <hi>Sodomites</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o were made Examples of Gods Eternal vengeance, to all perſecutors and ungodly men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſo in the caſe of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when the Lord manifeſted himſelf unto them by <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to worſhip contrary to the worſhip a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d wills of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and walked contrary to their wayes and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, and were oppreſſed and held in bondage, till God was provoked to deſtroy them, ſeeing his heavy Plagues and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts did not reform them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 14.</p>
            <p>And alſo the Judges and Kings of Iſrael, who were wicked, and did that which was evil in the ſight of the Lord, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not him, nor his way and people, how the Lord, the Moſt High God, dealt with them according to their doings, and how he often cut their dayes ſhort in the earth, and made their Names a reproach for ever.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the caſe of <hi>Haman,</hi> whom the King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> had exalted and given Power and Authority unto, how he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted over the Kings peaceable Subjects, and poor Jews miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenting, and falſly accuſing them to the King, becauſe <hi>Mordecai</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> could not give that honour to him, which belonged to the Lord; telling the King, <hi>That their Laws were divers from all people, and that they kept not the Kings Laws;</hi> and therefore ſaid, <hi>it was not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them:</hi> And the King giving too much credit unto this envious, bloody-minded man, conſented to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:56124:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>Jews,</hi> and bid him do as he would to them, and left them wholly to the mercy of a mercileſs man to deſtroy them; and in the Kings Name he began to proceed againſt the <hi>Jews;</hi> ſo that his Villany muſt be done in the Kings Name, which was his Cloak, and to execute the Kings Laws, (or that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive, unrighteous Decree which he through wicked Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had obtained) as if the King had ſworn him to do all miſchief in his Name; which would have been great diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the King, if he ſhould have brought his wicked inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to paſs; and would undoubtedly have provoked the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to anger againſt the King, to deſtroy him: But the Lord appearing for his innocent people, the Kings heart was turned, and he perſwaded from his Reſolution which he had made through miſ-information, and then ſee what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed this proud <hi>Haman,</hi> who was exalted as it were from the Dunghill to the Throne, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 3. 7.</p>
            <p>And again, how the Princes and Preſidents of King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> who fearing that Truth and Righteouſneſs ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted by <hi>Daniel;</hi> and De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eit and Wickedneſs thrown down, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y finding no occaſion againſt him, except it were concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w and Worſhip of his God, for they could not deny but he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s an honeſt peaceable man, and his converſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men was blameleſs and harmleſs; and what was the matter then? why did they perſecute him and throw him into the Lyons Den? Why theſe envious men that purpoſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him coming into his Chamber, and finding him ſeeking the Lord or making petitions to his God, as he uſe to do at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times, (notwithſtanding there was a Law made againſt it) with his window open, they went to ſtir up and incenſe the King againſt him, ſaying, <hi>Haſt thou not ſigned a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, That every man that ſhall ask a Petition of any God or Man, within thirty dayes, ſave of thee, O King, (or as thou haſt preſcribed) ſhall be caſt into the Lyons</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:56124:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Den; and here is one</hi> Daniel, <hi>who regardeth not thee, O King, nor the Decree that thou haſt ſigned; but makes his petitions three times a day,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. And this was his crime, for worſhipping God, or asking petitions of him, according to his uſual manner; but ſee the end of his Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers and Perſecutors, <hi>Jer.</hi> 24. And the King repealed that Law, in which he pleaſed God.</p>
            <p>And again, <hi>Iſaiah, Jeremiah,</hi> and others, were perſecuted by their own Nation the <hi>Jews,</hi> for bearing witneſs againſt their evil practiſes, by word and converſation, and becauſe they could not conform to their unrighteous Laws; yet the <hi>Jews</hi> pretended to worſhip the true God, and did profeſs love and ſervice to him in words; which ſome perhaps may think were more juſtifiable then thoſe Perſecutors before-mentioned, who worſhipped nothing elſe but Creatures, and the works of mens hands: But that cannot be; for perſecution for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and tender Conſcience ſake, in whomſoever it appeared, was never of God, nor practiſed by good men: And it is worſe, and more wicked in them who profeſs the true God, then in thoſe who neither know, nor own him in words; and a bare profeſſion of God, his Law and Ordinances, cannot justifie any man or people in the ſight of God, while that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſpirit rules in them, which leads to perſecution.</p>
            <p>And the chief Prieſts, Scribes and Phariſees, had a large Profeſſion of God and Scriptures, and had the Law of God read among them every Sabbath-day, and did many things which God commanded to be done, and yet perſecuted Chriſt that was the Subſtance; and ſaid <hi>they had a Law, and by their Law he ought to dye,</hi> Joh. 19. And his Apostles were alſo perſecuted by them as Blaſphemers, and ſuch as chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their Laudable Cuſtoms and Laws, and turners of the world upſide down; becauſe the Lord was with them, in whoſe Authority they preached the Goſpel, and ſtruck at the very
<pb facs="tcp:56124:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> root of Iniquity, Wickedneſs and Oppreſſion, and their vain Cuſtoms, which the people then could not endure to hear beat down; but the then Rulers commanded them to preach no more in the Name of Jeſus; and they gathered great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes together, ſometime by the Sea-ſide, on Mountains, Fields, and in upper Chambers, ſeparate from the <hi>Jews</hi> and Heathens Synagogues and Temples; and many did ſuffer great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by reaſon thereof. And thus in brief <hi>(Reader)</hi> thou mayeſt ſee and remember how righteous men that truly feared God, and wrought righteouſneſs in the earth, have been perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and cruelly intreated both by profeſſors and prophane.</p>
            <p>And as it was then, <hi>He that was born after the fleſh, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted him that was born after, and walked in the Spirit,</hi> even ſo it is now in this our day, wherein the God of Heaven hath appeared unto us, and viſited us in his everlaſting Love and Mercy, by the Light and Spirit of his Son Chriſt Jeſus, which we have received, and by which we are led into all Truth and Righteouſneſs, and from the filthy converſation and wayes of the world, to bear witneſs for God, his Way and Worſhip, as it is made manifeſt to us; becauſe of which we alſo have been perſecuted, and cruelly intreated, ſince the Lord gathered us to be a people; and many have dealt hardly with us, and roſe up against us for theſe twelve or fourteen years; and all ſorts of people, from the high profeſſor, to the prophane, that have been in power in the world, have puſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at us. But now more abundantly, and particularly, one <hi>William Armorer,</hi> a Juſtice ſo called, and his Abettors, as may be ſeen by this following Relation, who hath appeared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us in this Town of <hi>Reading,</hi> more like a Monſter in nature, then a man, and much leſs like a Chriſtian, though he would be ſo accounted, as alſo the reſt of our Perſecutors would: But their works do make him and them manifeſt; and according to their proceedings (which thou wilt here find
<pb facs="tcp:56124:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> gathered into as ſhort a compaſs as we could well, to keep the ſubſtance of things) thou mayeſt judge of him and them; for we deſire not to lay open the cruel dealing of our adverſaries farther then to relate their own actions; neither have we put a worſe face upon it, then it is really in it ſelf. But if it doth appear ugly, cruel and monſtrous, it is their own; we have not wronged them in one particular, that we know of; neither have we filled paper, to amplifie, with many words to make a large volume, to ſet out the cruelty of his and their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and how contrary it is to the known Laws of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but to leave that to thy ingenious underſtanding, as thou ſhalt read the Relation, to make up that which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities ſake we have omitted; and the reaſon why it has lain ſo long, and not been publiſhed, as many have both expected and deſired, was, becauſe we did not deſire to lay open his cruelty, or to make a noiſe of our ſufferings (for in that we have the infallible teſtimony and evidence of Gods Eternal Spirit in our Conſciences, that we ſuffer for well doing, and for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſake; we are fully ſatisfied in our ſelves, if it had been buried in Obiivions Grave) but would rather have him amend and repented; but ſeeing he ſtill continues to deal hardly and cruelly with us, and not only ſo, but miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents us, and falſly accuſeth us to many who do not know his proceedings againſt us, we cannot but bring theſe things to publike view, for the clearing of that bleſſed Truth and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony for which we ſuffer, and our innocency, which is deeply concerned herein, and to ſatisfie all people who have heard the rumour thereof; as alſo, that he may ſee and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what he hath done againſt us, and leave off his bad intents and work of Cruelty, and repent of them.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Reader,</hi> thou wilt find by this following Relation, That the chief Cauſe of this our Suffering, is, Becauſe we cannot ſvvear at all, it being forbidden by Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,
<pb facs="tcp:56124:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> whom we muſt hear in all things, and by his Apostles; and being inwardly perſwaded in our Conſciences by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, That we (as Chriſtians) ought not to ſwear in any caſe, (as the true Chriſtians have been heretofore) we dare not do it. And alſo, becauſe we meet together to ſeek God, to wait upon him, and to ask Petitions of him, as we uſe to do, with our doors open: Becauſe of this, we are accuſed as Plotters, breakers of the Kings Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thronged up in Priſons, and ſentenced to Baniſhment from the Land of our Nativity; and all the Crime they can find us guilty of, is, Becauſe we confeſs we meet to ſeek the Lord, or wait upon him; and this our Adverſaries accounts ſufficient ground to proceed againſt us; whereby it is fully manifeſt, That it is againſt the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Good, of Sobriety, of Truth and Righteouſneſs, that this old Spirit of <hi>Cain,</hi> of the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> of <hi>Haman,</hi> and of the cruel <hi>Jews,</hi> is riſen in <hi>William Armorer,</hi> and ſome others, who take occaſion againſt us, becauſe of the Law and Worſhip of our God; elſe he could have nothing againſt us, nor juſtly accuſe us; but becauſe he himſelf comes to our Meetings again and again, as thou wilt ſee, and finds us ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord, or asking Petitions of our God, and nothing elſe he can prove againſt us; for we can appeal to him, and all people in this place, Who we have wronged or hurt in any thing? And have we not lived peaceably, harmleſly, and honeſtly amongſt our Neighbours? And if nothing elſe can be found againſt us, but for the cauſe before mentioned, is it not great pity that any of the Rulers of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be ſo much like thoſe wicked Perſecutors before mentioned, as to have a hand in ſuch a work? And doth it not tend ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much to the diſhonour of the King, that ſuch things ſhould be acted in his Name? And do not ſuch men do the King much more hurt, then ever they can do him good, by
<pb facs="tcp:56124:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſobliging the hearts of all his beſt and moſt trueſt Subjects, by theſe wilful and rude Proceedings in his Name, and only ſatisfie the Rabble of rude deboiſt people, in whom his ſafety doth not at all conſiſt. To ſay no more, we ſhall leave it to the ſerious conſideration of the wiſe <hi>Reader,</hi> and remain friends unto him and all men, and do pray for the Converſion of our Enemies, who hate us, though we are continued under great Oppreſſion.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Priſoners called</hi> Quakers, <hi>in</hi> Reading-Gaol, <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 13th <hi>day of the</hi> 6th <hi>Month,</hi> 1667.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56124:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PERSEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TION appearing in its own Open Face,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>BEfore we come to ſpeak particularly of the Proceedings of <hi>William Armorer,</hi> we thought fit (as in its right place) to give a ſhort Relation of the Proceedings of <hi>George Thorn,</hi> in the time of his Mayoralty, in the year 1662, and how he acted his part againſt the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> being his known Neighbours in the Town of <hi>Reading.</hi> But he being ſince dead, we ſhall ſay the leſs of him, only for the ſake of ſuch as are yet living, that they may not tread in the footſteps of unwiſe and cruel-minded-men, and that thoſe that have had a hand in theſe things, may take warning, and repent, before the time cometh, when the wicked ceaſeth to act, and receiveth his reward accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his works, which follows him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>8th</hi> day of the ſecond Month, called <hi>April,</hi> 1662, the Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being holden at <hi>Newberry</hi> for the County of <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks,</hi> where <hi>Rich: Palmer</hi> of <hi>Oakingham,</hi> ſate Judg; where <hi>Thomas Curtis, George Lamboll,</hi> and eight more, appeared, being warned thither for not going to their Worſhip, an Indictment being read againſt them upon that account; They pleaded not guilty, and the Court requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them to put in Bail for their appearance the next Seſſions; one of them anſwered, They were known to them, and if they would take their words to appear, they would promiſe to appear; but that not being accepted, they were ſent to the Gaol</p>
            <p>The <hi>15th</hi> of the <hi>4th</hi> Month, called <hi>June,</hi> 1662, <hi>George Thorne,</hi> Mayor, ſent two Conſtables, <hi>Thomas White,</hi> and <hi>John Kenton,</hi> (both which alſo are ſince dead) to the Meeting at <hi>Tho: Curtis</hi> his houſe, and took the Names of Friends at the Meeting; and ſaid they muſt come before the Mayor the next morning: One of them anſwered,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56124:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> That they would not go out of the way on purpoſe, but might go if the Mayor did ſend for them. The next day the Conſtables and Officers with a Warrant from <hi>Geo: Thorne,</hi> took <hi>William Lamboll, William Tompſon, Anthony Sadler, Thomas Tudway, Walter Emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Joan Dee, Anne Hatt, Hanah Webb,</hi> and <hi>Sarah Lamboll,</hi> ſome in the ſtreet, ſome at their own houſes, and ſome going to their work; ſome of whom deſiring to go before the Mayor, being brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, he demanded bond of them to appear next Seſſions; they anſwered, They could promiſe to appear: But that not being taken, he ſent them to Gaol; and being brought to the Gaol-door, one of the Officers ſaid to the Under-keeper, <hi>Here I have brought you two ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men.</hi> But <hi>S. Lamboll,</hi> and <hi>H. Webb,</hi> were bailed by <hi>John M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les,</hi> unknown to them.</p>
            <p>The 22<hi>d</hi> of the ſame Month, <hi>George Thorn</hi> Mayor, and <hi>Thomas White</hi> Conſtable, came to the Meeting, and took Nineteen Friends, viz. <hi>Leo: Coale<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Joſeph Coale, Jonathan Lamboll, Thomas Chelton, Jo: Walker, Jo: Fellows, Joſeph Phips, Tho: Bartlet, Jo: Boult, James Whiteheart, Edw: Smith, Jo: Ranolds, Rich: Hutchins, Anne Sharp, Margery Richardſon, Eliz: Dee,</hi> Widow, <hi>Bridget Smith, Sarah Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boll,</hi> and <hi>Hannah Webb,</hi> and ſent them to the Gaol for being at the Meeting; <hi>Sarah Lamboll,</hi> and <hi>Hannah Webb</hi> being committed in the Town-Seſſions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>8th</hi> of the <hi>5th</hi> Month, called <hi>July,</hi> the Seſſions for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was holden at <hi>Abingdon,</hi> to which place the Priſoners before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned were brought, and the Aſſizes being the next day, the Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was adjourned for two weeks: the Priſoners not Called.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>18th.</hi> of the ſame Month, the Seſſions was holden for the <hi>Burrough</hi> of <hi>Reading,</hi> where <hi>Sarah Lambol</hi> and <hi>Henry Webb</hi> appeared: Inſtead of proceeding againſt them according to their Commitment, for being at a meeting; they asked them if they would take the Oath of Allegiance, which they for Conſcience ſake refuſing, were ſent to <hi>Goale</hi> again.</p>
            <p>And then the 22<hi>d</hi> of the ſame Month, the Priſoners before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, were had again to <hi>Abingdon</hi> to the Seſſions, being the time to which they before Adjourned, where 34 Priſoners appeared, ſome being left ſick at <hi>Goale;</hi> And <hi>Tho. Curtis</hi> and <hi>Geo. Lambol,</hi> and 7 of the other 8 that were Indicted at <hi>Newberry,</hi> for not going to their Worſhip (one of them being an ancient man, and not well, was left
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56124:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> behind at <hi>Reading)</hi> were tryed by the Jury, and freed. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, <hi>Tho: Holt</hi> the Judg, cauſed the Oath of Allegiance to be tendred to <hi>Tho: Curtis,</hi> and <hi>Geo: Lamboll,</hi> whereby to enſnare thoſe two only in that ſnare; for refuſing of which, they were committed again to Gaol; and of the other ſeven they demanded Sure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies for their good behaviour, which they not giving, were ſent likewiſe again to Gaol; and the other twenty five Priſoners (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quit by the Jury) were diſcharged.</p>
            <p>The <hi>27th</hi> of the ſame Month came <hi>Geo: Thorne</hi> Mayor, and <hi>Tho: Seikes</hi> Juſtice (ſo called) with <hi>Hugh Smith</hi> the Clerk, and many Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with them, to the Meeting, having the Statute-book with them alſo: One of the Friends deſired they would read the Preamble to the Oath; but they refuſing, took Forty ſeven Friends, viz. <hi>Tho: Noris, Tho: Tudway, Jo: Kemboll, Leo: Key, Joſeph Phips, William Lamboll, Jo: Ranolds, Chriſtopher Cheeſman, Walter Emerton, Humphrey E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merton, Tho: Bartlet, Jo: Walker, William Tompſon, Jo: Boult, James Whitheart, Jo: Jegger, William Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, Tho: Chelton, Jaſper May, Jo: Fellows, Antho: Sadler, Edw: Smith, Tho: Speed, William Whiſtler, Jonathan Lamboll, Ann Hatt, Francis Kent, Eliz: Tudway, Joan Wilesſby, Rachel Cope, Sarah Paine, Anne Weedon, Sarah Lamboll, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz: Dee Jane Huſſy, Joan Wheeler, Ann South, Hannah Wrenn, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah Emerton, Judith Smith, Bridget Smith, Hannah Mills, Anne Webb, Dorothy Clarke, Catherine Edſol, Francis Dawſon,</hi> and <hi>Joan Terrey,</hi> and made a Mittimus, and ſent them to the Gaol, many of whom were freed but a few days before, at <hi>Abingdon;</hi> as the Reader may obſerve.</p>
            <p>The <hi>7th</hi> of the <hi>8th</hi> Month, called <hi>October,</hi> 1662, the Seſſions was holden at <hi>Newberry;</hi> but all the Women were left at home by the Mayor's Order; there being ſo many, it may be the burden was too heavy for him to bear; ſo they were dropp'd, and taken no notice of: And <hi>Tho: Curtis,</hi> and <hi>George Lamboll</hi> were not had thither, but the ſeven men before mentioned, committed for not giving Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, were called and diſcharged; and the reſt of the men laſt taken, being there called, were indicted for being at an unlawfull Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and having pleaded Not guilty, the Court demanded Sureties; for not finding of which, they were ſent back again to Gaol.</p>
            <p>The <hi>13th</hi> day of the <hi>11th</hi> Month,—62, the Seſſions for the County was held at <hi>Reading,</hi> but none of our Friends (the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56124:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> were called, but were kept till the next Quarter-Seſſions hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at <hi>Newberry</hi> the <hi>28th</hi> of the ſecond Month called <hi>April,—</hi>63; and being had thither, twenty one in number being called into the Court, the Judg ſaid to them, <hi>You are diſcha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ged, and pray God bleſs you; but though we do diſcharge you, yet we cannot give away the Cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks fees:</hi> The Priſoners told them, they would ſpeak with the Clerk; which having done, told him they could give him no money; but however, he diſcharged them.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Geo: Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne</hi> Mayor, having thus g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven the onſet upon his peaceable and harmleſs Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghbours, for their tender Conſcience ſake, and having haled them to priſon, and thronged them together, and hurried them backward and forward from one Seſſions to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till his own works had even tired him, his fury being pretty much ſpent, another Inſtrument appeared to carry on that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rk, to wit, <hi>William Armorer,</hi> who came on with open mouth, as it were, as if he would have devoured at once, the ſheep of the Lords Paſture; and as if he had bid defiance to the Lord God of Iſrael, and were reſolved to deſtroy his choſen people, being furniſhed with great ſtrength and authority, and having his will for his Law, and priſons ready to receive all that come to his hand; or rather, what his own heart and hand found out, ſearching the Houſes, Chambers and Shops of innocent people for that end, as if it were Crime enough to be called a (Chriſtian) <hi>Quaker,</hi> and his puniſhment muſt far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the quality of the Crime, being almoſt three year and a half's Impriſonment: And thus he has continued to this time, as the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may obſerve.</p>
            <p>Upon the <hi>27th</hi> day of the firſt Month, in the Year 1664, <hi>William Armorer</hi> came to the houſe of <hi>Thomas Curtis</hi> (where the people of God were peaceably met together, to wait upon, and worſhip the Lord in Spirit and in Truth, according to their uſual manner) and pulled out of the Meeting the young children, then took thirty four men, whoſe Names are as followeth, viz. <hi>William Lamboll, Richard Hutchins, William Tompſon, Jaſper May, Edward Lambourn, John Fellow, James Marlow, Anthony Sadler, Thomas Tudway, Iames Whiteheart, Walter Emerton, Ioſeph Phipes, Tho: Speed, Tho: Chelton, Tho: Cenicke, Tho: Heifeild, Tho: Hinde, Daniel Green, Henry Pizeing, Iames Lavell, Hen: Briſtow, Rob: Pider, Tho: Curtis, Geo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boll, Leonard Key, Iohn Kembell, Ionathan Lamboll, Leo: Coale, Io:</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:56124:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Paine, Iohn Becke, Tho: Norris, Edward Fellow, William Whiſtler,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Page;</hi> and cauſed the Clerk to make a Mittimus, the ſubſtance whereof was, for being at an unlawful meeting, contrary to an Act of Parl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ament made about a year or two before, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and delivered them to <hi>Richard Iohnſon,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Creed,</hi> Conſtables, who had them to the County-Gaol in <hi>Reading.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 3<hi>d.</hi> day of the 2<hi>d</hi> Month called <hi>April,</hi> 1664, came <hi>William Armorer</hi> again to the meeting, and took two men, <hi>viz. Robert Paine,</hi> and <hi>John Bolt,</hi> being all the men that were at the meeting; And ſaid to them, what a Devil, are you met again? I will ſend you all to Priſon; what a Devil, are you all Dumb? hath the Devil caſt his Club over you, and bewitched you? <hi>I. Boult</hi> ſaid, We have learned of a better Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, even the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus, which teacheth us to deny the Devil and all his Inſtruments. <hi>William Armorer,</hi> Who a Devil will believe you? hang you, you are deluded by the ſpirit of the Devil; I will ſend you all to Priſon: <hi>I. Boult,</hi> Many good people will believe us, and we wholly deny the ſpirit of the Devil, having choſen a better ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rit, the ſpirit of Chriſt Jeſus, which is a ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of love and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of patience and humility. <hi>W.</hi> A. You ſay true, it is ſo. <hi>I. B.</hi> And the ſpirit of the Divil is an angry, furious, haſty, perſecuting ſpirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>W. A.</hi> ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d he is ſo: <hi>I. B.</hi> Come, let us try who is of this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, thee, or us. <hi>W. Armorer,</hi> A Devil on you, I could find in my heart to lay you over the pate with my Cane. <hi>I. Boult,</hi> I hou oughteſt to keep the peace, and I hope thou wilt not go to break it; did'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t thee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read that Chriſt, or any of his Apoſtles did Perſecute any? <hi>W. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er,</hi> Did none? then Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſts flock is but a little flock, and there is but a few of you, but I will make you fewer, I will hunt you out, and ſend you to Priſon. <hi>I. Boult,</hi> that's the weakeſt thing that thou can'ſt do; if thou can'ſt convince me of any thing that is evil, I will hear thee and let the Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons alone: after ſome other diſcourſe he cauſed a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttimus to be made, and ſent them to <hi>Goale:</hi> And the <hi>19th</hi> day of the ſame Month the General Quarter Seſſions for the County was held at <hi>Newbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> but the Priſoners before mentioned were no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had thither, nor Called; neither at the Seſſions for the Burrough of <hi>Reading,</hi> held about the ſame time, though moſt of them were Inhabitants of the ſame Corporation.</p>
            <p>The Firſt of the 3<hi>d</hi> Month called <hi>May,</hi> 1664, came <hi>William Armorer</hi> again to the Meeting, and took one man and ſix women, viz.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56124:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Tho. Bartlet, Anne Hat, Anne Sharp, Hanah Webb, Sarah Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy Clarke,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth Crage,</hi> and made a Mittimus much after the manner of the former, and ſent them to <hi>Goal</hi> by <hi>Rich. Iohnſon</hi> Conſtable.</p>
            <p>The <hi>8th</hi> of the ſame Month, came <hi>W. Armorer</hi> to the Meeting again, there being no man there, he took ſeven women, <hi>Bridget Smith, Anne Curtis, Sarah Lambol, Iudeth Smith, Katharine Woodard Martha Cheeſeman</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth Hampon;</hi> and made a Mittimus as before, and ſent them to <hi>Goale,</hi> by <hi>Tho. Coats</hi> Conſtable.</p>
            <p>Upon the 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>d</hi> of the ſame Month, <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lliam Armorer</hi> came again, to the Meeting in great fury, as formerly, but finding only a few Children and young Maidens, he pulled them out himſelf, (and his men) having a great Club, or Staff in his hand, ſtruck one of the Maidens a ſore Stroke, that ſhe felt it for ſome time after; and told them he would ſend them to Priſon; and other throatning ſpeeches what he would do to them, if they came there again: And on the ſeventh of the fourth month, the Gaoler called for all the Women and Maids before-mentioned, except ſix, <hi>viz. Ann Hatt, Ann Curtis, Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ah Lamboll, A. Sharp, Sarah Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne,</hi> and <hi>Eliz. Crage,</hi> and gave them leave to go out of priſon, and to come again when he ſent for them, having (as is ſuppoſed) ſome private Inſtruction from <hi>William Armorer</hi> ſo to do; and about the <hi>18th</hi> day of the ſame month, <hi>Tho: Coates</hi> Conſtable, came to the Gaol, and fetcht out one of thoſe ſix <hi>(Anne Sharp)</hi> alſo, the Gaoler demanding fees of her Husband, he refuſed to pay it; notwithſtanding his refuſal, ſhe was ſet at liberty, for the Conſtable had ſome work for her Husband to do.</p>
            <p>And now we come to the Proceedings at the General Quarter-Seſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns held at <hi>Abingdon</hi> the <hi>12th</hi> of the <hi>5th</hi> month, 1664, againſt the Priſoners before mentioned, who were taken up, and committed for being at meetings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But being brought to the place afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, they were informed that the Juſtices would have put them off to the Seſſions for the Burrough of <hi>Reading,</hi> but <hi>William Armorer</hi> would not conſent to it; and one <hi>Herſie</hi> told <hi>Champion</hi> the Deputy-Clerk, That here was about threeſcore <hi>Quakers,</hi> and asked what he ſhould do with them: <hi>Champion</hi> replyed, That he would ſhew them a trick; which he endeavoured to do indeed, becauſe ſome of the moderat'ſt men who were warned to be of the Jury, were except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56124:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> againſt, and put out; becauſe ſome of our friends about a year before, being there upon the ſame account of meeting, were clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Jury, there being no ſufficient evidence againſt them. Well, in the Afternoon they were called to the Barr, expecting a Trial according to their Mittimus: One Friend, <hi>James Whiteheart,</hi> being the firſt that was called to the Barr, putting not off his Hat to them, they were very angry with him, and many words paſſed, and he was taken from the Barr, but they never ſo much as asked him whether he would take th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Oath of Allegiance, or not. The next that was called, was one <hi>Henry Pizeing,</hi> (who was committed among them; but was no <hi>Quaker,</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> called) who coming to the Barr with his Hat in his hand, and bowing his body to them, <hi>Tho: Holt</hi> (who was Judg) ſaid, <hi>Here's a man hath ſome manners;</hi> and asked him if he would take the Oath of Allegiance? He anſwered, he had taken it twice already: The Judg ſaid, <hi>But y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u were no</hi> Quaker then; The ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> replyed, <hi>Neither am I now; but have been many weeks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and I nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſaw no hurt by them, but are an hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, civil people:</hi> Upon which <hi>William Armore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſtood up, and ſaid to him, <hi>Why did you not tell me ſo before. Henry</hi> ſaid, <hi>Your Worſhip was ſo wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that you would not hear me.</hi> Then the Judg ſaid he muſt take it again; ſo the Oath was read to him, and he ſaid after them; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken the Oath, the Judg ſtood up, and made a motion to the reſt of the Juſtices, That becauſe this <hi>Henry Pizeing</hi> had taken the Oath, he did deſire that they would conſent that he ſhould go free without paying any fees; to which the Juſtices conſenting, bid the Gaoler take no fees of him, and would have had him to have paſt out at a back door, and come no more among the Quakers. But he told them, He hoped now he was freed, he might go out at which door he would.</p>
            <p>Then the Judg bid the Gaoler bring up ten of the Priſoners at a time; and <hi>Tho: Norris,</hi> and ſeveral others, were called; and they asked them whether they would take the Oath of Allegiance; they anſwered, they were not committed upon the account of the Oath, but were taken at a meeting, and expected a Trial upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: Others of them anſwered, Chriſt had commanded them not to ſwear at all, and therefore they could not take an Oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h; and that they were not ſent to Gaol for that, but were taken at a meeting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Judg. <hi>We diſcharge you as to your meeting, but you muſt take the</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:56124:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Oath of Allegiance.</hi> Many being called, anſwered to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as the former. <hi>Tho: Curtis</hi> was called; the Judg asked him if he would take the Oath of Allegiance? Who anſwered, He had ſomething to ſay, and deſired he might be heard; and ſaid he did not refuſe the Oath upon the account as not to bear his Allegiance to the King, but becauſe Chriſt had commanded him not to ſwear at all; for he was perſwaded, That he had manifeſted himſelf to be as good a Subject to the King, as moſt in the County, ſince He came in; and that if he could take any Oath either to ſave his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate or Life, he did profeſs he would begin with that Oath; and therefore deſired that the Court would be pleaſed to let ſome of their Miniſters ſhew him by the Scr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ptures how he might take it, and not break the Command of Chriſt, and he would do it. The Judg called to a Miniſter that was near them, to ſpend half a quarter of an hours time with him, to ſatisfie him in this particular, and they would ſit ſtill and hear. But the Prieſt (one <hi>Worell,</hi> as we remember his Name was) ſaid, putting off his Hat, and bowing to the Court, he deſired to be excuſed, for he had, had to do with ſome of them already, and they were an obſtinate people, and would not be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, or to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho: Curtis:</hi> This is commonly the anſwer we have from theſe men, when they are deſired to anſwer us a queſtion according to the Scripture, that we might be ſatisfied; they anſwer, We are obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, or ſuch like.</p>
            <p>So the Gaoler was commanded to take them all away, by <hi>William Armorer,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>I know they will not take it;</hi> though many of them never denyed it.</p>
            <p>The next morning, being the <hi>13th</hi> of the month aſoreſaid, after <hi>William Armorer</hi> was gone out of Town, two Friends, viz. <hi>Richard Billingſly,</hi> and <hi>William Sargood,</hi> were called to the Barr (being war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to appear there for not going to their Church, though there was no Prieſt in the Pariſh) and expected they ſhould have been proceeded againſt for that; inſtead of which, they asked them if they would take the Oath of Allegiance; and becauſe they could not ſwear, were ſent to Gaol with the Priſoners before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
            <p>The <hi>19th</hi> of the ſame month, <hi>John Cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> Conſtable, came with a warrant from <hi>William Armorer,</hi> to the Gaoler, and demanded the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56124:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> body of <hi>Tho: Curtis;</hi> which being delivered by the Gaoler, was had to the Bear Inne, where <hi>William Armorer</hi> was, who ſaid to <hi>Tho: Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tis, You are going eo Briſtol Fair, but I will ſtop your journey,</hi> (the Sherif having given him leave to go to <hi>Briſtol</hi> about his occaſions) and commanded the Conſtable to carry him to the Town-Priſon, the Counter; he refuſing to go, (being a Priſoner in the County-Gaol, the Conſtable called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Officer, and compelled him; and they had him to the Counter without <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the 22<hi>d</hi> of the ſame month, being Seſſions time for the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough of <hi>Reading, Rich: Johnſon</hi> Conſtable, came and fetcht out <hi>Tho: Curtis</hi> from the Counter, before <hi>Tho: Seikes</hi> Mayor, and <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Armorer, Edward Dolby,</hi> Juſtices, and many others in the Council-Chamber: The <hi>Mayor</hi> asked him, Whether he ſent thoſe Papers? T. <hi>C.</hi> ſaid, <hi>I received them from a little Maid that came from the Gaol, and I ſent them:</hi> They ſaid, <hi>But did you write them?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>Nay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Did you indite them,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Mayor? I will not anſwer to ſuch queſtions,</hi> (ſaid T. <hi>C.) read the Paper, and then I will ſay more to it.</hi> So they gave him the Paper, and he read it; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reading that part which ſaith, <hi>Becauſe of ſwearing, the Land mourns;</hi> Alderman <hi>Johnſon</hi> ſaid, <hi>that was vory true:</hi> And having read it, T. <hi>C.</hi> ſaid it was every word true, and ſhould ſtand for ever; and he did own it: Then ſaid <hi>VVilliam Armorer, I will ſend it to the Council.</hi> T. C. ſaid, <hi>I would they had every one, one of them:</hi> A Copy of which here follows.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="paper">
                        <p>THE Eternal God, from whom no ſecrets can be hid, ſees your doings, and the eye of the Lord beholds the way that now you walk in, and the works you are about, who are perſecuting his Lambs, and impr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſoning his people, who for the fulfilling of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and walking in his ways, have choſen the ſufferings of this preſent world, rather then all the glory and pleaſure that this world can afford them; and we have counted up our coſt, and do find up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſerious deliberation, That it is better for us to dye by the hands of the hard-hearted and cruel men of this world, in and under the favour, love and friendſhip of the Lord, then to loſe our peace with him, by making ſhipwrack of our faith and peace of conſcience
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56124:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> which the Lord hath given us; and we have truly debated, ponder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and conſidered this our preſent ſtate of hard and cruel ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our own boſomes; and weigh'd our hearts in the ballance of Gods truth; and there is nothing in all this world that could make us to leave our Wives and Families, our Callings, Eſtates and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, but this very thing, namely, The Truth of our God, and the Worſhip of Chriſt Jeſus; the profeſſion and practiſe of which, at this day is the ground of this our ſufferings. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you preſs us ſo hard to take the Oath of Allegiance, and come to your Church; We do declare in the ſincerity of our hearts, That the ground and cauſe why we cannot take an Oath in any caſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be to the loſs of our Eſtates and Life, is, Becauſe Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles hath commanded us not to ſwear at all, and it is not lawful for us in any caſe to break Chriſts command: And if any of your Miniſters, Doctors, Prieſts or Biſhops, can make it appear by Gods Word, or the Scriptures, that it's lawful for us to ſwear, and may ſwear, and not fall into damna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ion, we will take it. And therefore ceaſe calling for us to ſwear, and break Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, till your Doctors, Biſhops, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>rates, or Miniſters, or ſome of them, hath convinced us that it may be done, and Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand not broken. There is too much ſwearing already, and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſwearing, the Land mourns.</hi> And as concerning coming to your Church, we have with much gravity conſidered the true ſtate of the Church of which you are members, to ſee if poſſible, we might come to you, and join with you, and not loſe our peace with God; and this we find, That you have called your ſelves by the Name of the Church of Chriſt, but the nature of Chriſtians, and of the Church of Chriſt, is denyed by you: For the Pride we dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, and the Oaths we daily hear from the Members of your Church, is ſufficient to make a Heathen or a Turk (much more a Chriſtian) quite out of love with it: And further<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the cruelty that is practiſed by your members, as haling men and women out of their peaceable Meetings, and caſting them into Priſon, contrary to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt's Practiſe and Doctrine, is ground enough for us to believe that you are neither members of Chriſts Church, nor children of God, nor heirs of his bleſſed Kingdom; for if you were members of Chriſts Church, you would not act ſuch high bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemies againſt the living God, as to ſwear by the Blood and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56124:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> Wounds of God, and God damn me, and God confound me; and when you have ſo done, enter in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o your Church, and cry aloud, <hi>We beſeech thee to hear us goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d;</hi> and this is top, common among the members of your Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now in the coolneſs of your hearts, con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ider what it is you ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſo earneſtly pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſwading us unto: How ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> we come among <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>u, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d joy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> in prayer with ſuch as act this gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> wickedneſs? If we ſhould come and join with you, the Lord migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>mn us all together, for it is the ſame tongue, the ſame lips, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he ſame ſpirit that ſwears before you enter, that when you are entr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d, ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>s to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>od to hear you; ſo that the words of the Apoſtle are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>lled, <hi>Out of the ſame mouth p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>oceedeth bleſſings and curſings.</hi> Oh ye unw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>! ye know not God, neither of what ſpirit you are; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ore be adviſed before it is too late; for in love to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s do we declare unto you, That if you will have us joy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> to you your way muſt be to joyn to the Lord, repent of the wickedneſs that you have done, and return to the Lord God, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> away the evil of your doings, and caſt out from among you the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oud<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Drunkard, the Swearers, the Murderers, the Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and Whoremongers, and all other filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit that is amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>g you; and then clothe your ſelves with meekneſs and pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s the Church of Chriſt was in the dayes of the Apoſtles; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> if we will not joyn with you, and come to your Church, let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ur b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ame be upon our heads; for till then, although you call your ſelves Chriſtians, you are but Antichriſts ſervants, that oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Chriſt in this the day of his appearance. And though you may comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>l b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> force and cruelty, many to joyn with you in words, you do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but make them ten-fold more the children of the Devil, and a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ouſand-fold more in a capacity to do you miſchief; and truly ſuch Chriſtians; you have enough already; and this was the way that your forefathers walked in whom God overthrew, and razed their Name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ut of the Land of the living.</p>
                        <p>Therefore boaſt not your ſelves over us, as if the Lord had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken us, becauſe we have none in the Earth to take our part, or p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ead our cauſe; or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> if your day ſhould never have an end, or as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he Lord had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o regard to his ſuffering-people, nor took no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e of your cruelty towards them, for certainly, when we have fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ed up the meaſure of the ſufferings of Chriſt that is yet to be filled up, and you have filled up the meaſure of your cruelty and hard-heartedneſs,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56124:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Lord will divide between cattel and cattel, and you ſhall not eſcape his fierce Vengeance and fiery Indignation; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in love to your ſouls do we ſend this, that you might be warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before it is too late; <hi>for the wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, and all that forget God,</hi> as the Scripture plainly declareth, and we cannot but be plain with you. And therefore fear the Lord ye Rulers, and give glory to his Name, for the Lords day is at hand that ſhall burn as an oven, and the wicked ſhall be as thorns caſt into it, we wiſh you well and could rejoyce to ſee you in that path that leads you to Gods kingdom, that your ſouls might find reſt, that the light of the Lord might be your leader, and you might be guided up to God, is the deſire of them who in ſcorne are called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>From the Gaol,</hi> 
                              <date>
                                 <hi>the</hi> 22d <hi>of the fifth Month,</hi> 1664.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And the 31 of the <hi>5th</hi> Month, called <hi>July, William Armorer</hi> came again to the Meeting, and took ſeven Women and Maids, viz. <hi>Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get Smith, Eliz: Bradbridg, Anne Watſon, Anne Sharp, Eliz: Wright, Eliz: Dee</hi> the younger, and <hi>Sarah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtell,</hi> and cauſed his Clerk to make a Mittimus there preſent in the Meeting-room, mean while <hi>William Armorer</hi> his man, <hi>John Venter,</hi> knowing that <hi>Tho: Curtis,</hi> his Wife and Man-ſervant, were all Priſoners, went and opened a door, and went into the houſe, (there being only a Maid-ſervant, and one man of the Family, not very well in his chamber, having taken ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that morning) and went up ſtairs, meeting with the Maid, bid her not be afraid, and asked her if there were any in the Houſe more then the Family? who anſwered, No; of which he inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Maſter; being gone out of doors again, the Maid lockt the door; in a little time after, his Maſter, <hi>William Armorer,</hi> went and knockt at the door; the Maid being in a fear, her Maſter, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſs, and Man-ſervant being all in the Gaol, did not open the door. But <hi>William Armorer</hi> pull'd ſome kind of Inſtrument out of his Pocket, and pickt the Lock, entered the houſe, and ſearched from room to room, and under the bed, until he came where the man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Houſe was, and asked his Name; he told him his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56124:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Name was <hi>Joſeph Coale;</hi> and being asked where he dwelt, anſwered, That he dwelt there, and that he had lived there for ſeven years at times, and that it was the place of his abode: So <hi>William A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>morer</hi> began to turn about, as if he would have gone away; but his Man <hi>Venter</hi> turned to him, ſaying, <hi>Sir, this is he we were informed of:</hi> His Maſter ſaid, <hi>Is this he indeed? Sir,</hi> ſaid <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enter, this is the man, this is</hi> Coale. Then <hi>William A morer</hi> took him by the arm, and bid him come with him: <hi>J. C.</hi> ſaid, <hi>Whither muſt I go? Go!</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Gaol. To Gaol!</hi> (ſaid <hi>J. C.) for what? what have I done? W. Armorer</hi> ſaid, <hi>I will tell you for what;</hi> and being pulling of him down ſtairs, ſaid, <hi>Will you take the Oath of Allegiance? Joſ.</hi> ſaid, <hi>Why doſt thou ask me ſuch a queſtion? I am known in the Town, having ſerved an appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhip in it, and am a free-man of it, and have not been uſed to ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but if thou canſt convince me by ſound reaſons and arguments, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures, that I may ſafely, and not break Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, I may do it.</hi> But <hi>W. A.</hi> ſaid, <hi>Ile ſend you to Gaol, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e you ſhall convince your ſelf;</hi> and ſo put two lines more in the Womens Mittimus, for refuſing the Oath of Allegiance to His Majeſty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſent him to the Houſe of Correction with the ſeven women be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, by <hi>John Creed</hi> Conſtable, who in a ſhort time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dyed; and the next day <hi>W. Armorer</hi> ſent for <hi>J. C.</hi> and asked him the ſame queſtions, and after ſome diſcourſe about the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unlawfulneſs of Swearing, ſent him back again to the houſe of Correction.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſecond day of the ſixth Month, called <hi>Auguſt, William Armorer</hi> came again to the Meeting in a violent manner, and took one man, and ſeven women, viz <hi>William Yeet, Anne Ball, Mary Slade, Mary Emerton, Elizabeth Lavell, Katharine Edſol, Ellin Binfeild,</hi> and <hi>Margery Richardſon,</hi> and ſent them to the Houſe of Correction.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>14th</hi> of the ſame Month, <hi>William Armorer</hi> came again; and though there were but two men and one woman, viz. <hi>Benjamin Coale, John Trayard, Hannah Webb,</hi> as he judged, above the age of ſixteen years; yet thoſe three, (contrary to the Act, which allows of four to meet) he ſent with a Mittimus, the ſubſtance whereof was, For being at an unlawful Meeting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>Thomas Coates,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, to the Houſe of Correction; and while the Clerk was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Mittimus, he went to the houſe of <hi>Thomas Curtis</hi> again,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56124:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> and finding the door lockt (the maid being gone to carry ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion to her Maſter and Miſtris in priſon) he pickt the lock, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the doors, and went into the Court, the door of the houſe being lockt alſo, he pul'd out his pen-knife or ſome ſuch like inſtrument, to cut the key-hole, that he might come at the lock, to open it, till a neighbour that was deſired to look to the houſe in the maids ahſence, came to him, and told him there was no body in the houſe, and asked him what he did mean to break folkes houſe up, and pick the locks, and much more to that purpoſe? for he had been in the ware-houſe, where was much cloath, and one that ſaw him go, bid him take heed, for if any thing were loſt, it might be laid to his charge; then he (the ſaid <hi>William Armore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>)</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Woman</hi> in great wrath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What have you to do with it? where is that whore? (meaning that maid ſervant) and ſaid he would have her to morrow; the woman anſwered, ſhe was gone to carry her Maſter and Miſtris ſome victuals for ought ſhe knew; and having ſpoken very much to him for picking of the Locks, and what he had done; he was very angry, and asked her what ſhe had to do with it; who anſwered, ſhe had to do with it, for ſhe was to ſee that no body did ſteal any thing out of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>25th</hi> of the <hi>6th</hi> Month called <hi>Auguſt; William Armorer</hi> ſent for the four men from the Houſe of Correction, to witt, <hi>Jo: Coale, Benjamin Coale, William Yeet, John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ray,</hi> and <hi>Tho: Seik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> the Mayor, being with them; they asked them if they would take the Oath? they deſired to know for what they had lain ſo long in the Houſe of Correction: But they taking no notice of that, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>r ſome diſcourſe, and many railing accuſations breathed out by <hi>William Armorer,</hi> they committed them to the Gaol; and the ſame da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he women being ſent for, they put Fines on them; for non-payment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they ſent them back again to the Houſe of Correction, there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o remain till three months were expired.</p>
            <p>Upon the <hi>28th</hi> of the ſame month, <hi>William Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rer</hi> came to the Meeting again, and took four women, and cauſed a Mittimus to be made for them, viz. <hi>Anne H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rriſon, Hannah Emerton, Katharine Woodard,</hi> and <hi>Jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th Smith,</hi> and ſent them to the Houſe of Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though there were but four, which according to that Law, by which he pretended he proceeded, was a lawful Meeting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and at the ſame time he ſtruck a young Lad, who was under age, with a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56124:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> great Cane, and another time pull'd him by the Noſe, ſo that his Noſe was much ſwelled: And farther, he ſaid he would have the man and maid of <hi>Thomas Curtis</hi> to morrow, or elſe the Devil ſhould take him; which though he performed not, yet in ſome ſhort time it came in part to paſs; for he having ſent <hi>T. C.</hi> and his Wife and man-ſervant to priſon, and being kept cloſe priſoners, <hi>T. C.</hi> ſent into the Countrey for another man that was formerly his Apprentice, to look to his ſhop; and though he came not to the Meeting, yet his enmity and mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce was ſo great againſt <hi>T. C.</hi> and that Family, that the 31 of the ſame Month, he ſent two Officers with a Warrant, by force to take the man ſervant out of the ſhop, and bring him before him; for he had provided a ſnare for him, and had gotten <hi>Thomas Seikes</hi> the Mayor, (who hath heen very active alſo, in this work of cruelty) and being brought before them, they asked him if he would take the Oath of Allegiance: To which the ſaid man, <hi>Rob: Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock,</hi> anſwered, <hi>I am a peaceable man, and have wronged no man, and cannot break Chriſts commands, but can promiſe to be true to the King, and will be content to ſuffer the ſame puniſhment, if I break my promiſe, as they do who ſwear and break it:</hi> But notwithſtanding, the Mayor, and <hi>William Armorer,</hi> cauſed a Mittimus to be made, and ſent him to Gaol a ſo; and the ſame Officers asked a Neighbour where the Maid was, that he might have inſnared her alſo: for <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Armorer</hi> had ſaid (if not ſworn) but a little before, That he would ſend the Maid to Gaol, (or he would be hanged) and nayl up the doors, that there ſhould be no more meetings.</p>
            <p>And the ſame day was three women brought before <hi>W. Armorer,</hi> from the Houſe of Correction, who told them they were fined for being at a Meeting; and although the Act ſaid five pounds a piece, yet he had fined them but five ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llings a piece, and asked them if they would pay it? One of them, <hi>Anne Harriſon,</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>Thou haſt got our houſe already, that we built, and haſt taken away our means, and wouldſt thou have me pay more money when I have broke no Law? We were but four above the age of ſixteen years, and the</hi> Act <hi>ſays it muſt be above four. William Armorer</hi> ſaid his man told him they were ſix, and two of them run away, one was <hi>Frances Kent,</hi> the other <hi>Pidg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> maid. <hi>It is falſe</hi> (ſaid Anne Harriſon) <hi>there was</hi> Frances Kent, <hi>but ſhe was fetcht out of Town (being a Midwife) and as for the other, ſhe was not there; there was but four.</hi> W. Armorer ſaid, <hi>I ſhall have</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56124:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Mrs.</hi> Kent, <hi>and then let the beſt Lady in the Land want her, ſhe ſhall not go, except the King or Court ſend for her; but ſaid he could make as good a Midwife himſelf, as ſhe:</hi> So he ſent them back again to the Houſe of Correction, being comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tted for three months, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed them in two weeks after.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>18th</hi> of the <hi>7th</hi> month, called <hi>September,—</hi>64, <hi>William Armorer</hi> came to the meeting, and took one man and five women, viz. <hi>Chriſtopher Cheeſeman, Anne Sharp, Hannah Webb, Bridget Smith, Hannah Emerton, Judith Smith,</hi> and being brought to his own houſe, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore himſelf and <hi>Tho: Seikes,</hi> they fined them twelve pence a piece; for non-payment of which, he told them he would ſend them to the Gaol, and make them pay their Fees, which would be more; ſo he ſent them to the Gaol, but they were releaſed the next day.</p>
            <p>The <hi>4th</hi> of the <hi>8th</hi> month, called <hi>October,—</hi>64, the Seſſions for the County was held at <hi>Newberry,</hi> to which place about fifty Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſome of their Wives (who being all Priſoners upon the account of the Oath of Allegiance) were brought, and being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Barr, an Indictment was read againſt them, for obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſing to take the Oath of Allegiance; and the Clerk (one <hi>Champion)</hi> had ſworn that it was tendered to them at <hi>Abingdon,</hi> though many of them had never denyed to take it, and one was not ſo much as asked whether he would take it or not: The Priſoners being informed that <hi>William Armorer,</hi> and <hi>Tho: Seikes</hi> Mayor of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> ſuppoſing that the late Act, which ſaith, <hi>If any man ſhall refuſe to take an Oath in any Court of Judicature, being lawfully tendered (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Court-Leets) ſhall be tranſported &amp;c.</hi> ſuppoſing they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to take the Oath, might have made ſhort work with them, and to have run them all on this hazard, to be rid of them all at once; and the Judg of the Seſſions, a bad man, one <hi>Procter</hi> of <hi>Windſor,</hi> gave in his Charge, That it was Treaſon to refuſe the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. But the Indictment being read, they pleaded not guilty; ſome of their Adverſaries ſuppoſing (as ſome of the Priſoners were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) they would not have pleaded, and ſo they might have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them as Mutes; but having pleaded, and deſired a Copy of their Indictment, ſome of the Juſtices ſaid, <hi>God forbid but they ſhould have it:</hi> yet <hi>Procter</hi> the Judg would not conſent to it, till he had been at <hi>London,</hi> and asked the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hide,</hi> (as he ſaid) and if
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56124:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> he ſaid they ſhould have it, and the Law would afford it, they ſhould have it: Then one of the Juſtices asked him, <hi>Whether they were not admitted Council in ſuch a caſe?</hi> He ſaid, Yes. Then ſaid the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, <hi>How can they adviſe with Council, if they have not a Copy of their Indictment?</hi> So the Priſoners ſent one (being a Councellor) after them for a copy of their Indictment, and <hi>Champion</hi> the Clerk demanded 21 l. 13 s. 4 d. before he could grant it; but with ſome importunity it was gained for 1 l. 4 s. for one man and his Wife. And after the firſt were called, the other ſix that were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſince upon the ſame account, were called; being asked if they would ſwear, they deſired to ſpeak ſomething concerning their commitment, and how illegally <hi>William Armorer</hi> had proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, one being taken out of his Maſters Shop, another out of his Chamber not being well; another poor man out of his Shop from his labour; the others for being at a meeting where three were together, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but they would not admit them to ſpeak, but ſoon put them by, and they were all ſent back again to the Gaol.</p>
            <p>Again the <hi>6th</hi> of the <hi>8th</hi> month, called <hi>October,—</hi>64, <hi>W. Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> came to the meeting and took five women, viz. <hi>Anne Sharp, Fra: Kent, Eliz: Streater, Anne South,</hi> and <hi>Sarah Binfield,</hi> and ſent them to Gaol with a Mittimus for one night: But while he was in the meeting-room, a neighbours Wife perceiving the doors of the houſe of <hi>Tho: Curtis</hi> to be unlockt, went and locked a door, and carried away the key; which when <hi>W. Armorer</hi> came to underſtand that one had lockt the door, fell a ſwearing like a mad man; and a little time after they were gone out, they ſhut the ſtreet-door, the Womans daughter bringing the key of the inner door, <hi>W. Armorer</hi> his man <hi>Venter,</hi> by violence took it from her; but the ſtreet-door being ſhut, he could not get in: Then in great rage <hi>W. Armorer</hi> called for ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to break open the door; and ſome Hammer or Sledg, or ſuch like thing, being brought, they went about to do it; but others per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded <hi>W. Armorer</hi> (to pacifie him) that there was another way into the Houſe.</p>
            <p>The 23<hi>d</hi> of the ſame month came <hi>W. Armorer</hi> again to the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to his uſual manner, and took three men and ſix wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, viz. <hi>Chriſto: Cheeſeman, Ranold Ave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, Tho: Hine, Mary Wrenn, Eliz: Dee</hi> Widow, <hi>Jane Huſſy, Judeth Smith, Katharine Edſoll,</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56124:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Eliz: Lavell</hi> younger; and committed <hi>C. Cheeſeman</hi> on the third ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, though it was but his ſecond, and accuſed them of carrying of Letters about the Countrey, and then came together on that day to plot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But when they came to have their trial, then that is not mentioned; but the main buſineſs is to prove they were, there to worſhip God, or to ſeek God, or to ſeek Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this is the crime for which they proceed againſt them to <hi>Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> (as will more fully appear by the following Relation) and not a word of plotting then when they come to the proof: And the reſt were ſent to the Houſe of Correction for forty eight hours, <hi>Tho: Curtis</hi> his maid-ſervant being one of them: So that the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily were now priſoners, the maid being taken out of her maſters houſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>6th</hi> of the <hi>9th</hi> month, called <hi>November,—</hi>64, <hi>William Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morer</hi> came again to the meeting, and ſwore there was a goodly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; and cauſed the children to be pulled out, and with a ſtaff that had a goad, or ſome ſharp peick at the end of it, pricked ſome of them, that they were very ſore and black where he pricked them; and took one man and ſix women, viz. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. Hine, Anne Harriſon, Rachel Cape, Hannah Emerton, Mary Sanders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce Milerd, Mary Winter,</hi> and ſent them to the Houſe of Correction for three dayes.</p>
            <p>And the firſt of the tenth month, called <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mber,—</hi>64<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>William Armorer</hi> came again to the meeting, and cauſed the children to be pulled out, telling them he had a ſtick at home that he had forgot, would make them feel him, which was ſuppoſed to be the ſame with which he prick'd them before; being under age; he cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d not have his will in impriſoning of them: Others of the children he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to have forely whipt; and having turned them going, took two ancient Women, <hi>Bridget Smith,</hi> and <hi>Margery Richa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dſon,</hi> and ſent them to the Gaol on the third account; and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t four; viz. <hi>Anne Hatt, Margery Symonds, Grace Hutchins, Jane Huſſy,</hi> to the Houſe of Correction for twenty four hours: And being not ſatisfied when he had got them in priſon, but would have had the Gaoler put them in one room together, and no body to come at them; and what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions was brought them, ſhould be put in at the Grates; and hath cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d their papers to be taken from them, pretending they had ſent a Paper to the King and Council, which was very falſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:56124:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>And now we come to the proceedings of the ſaid</hi> William Armorer, <hi>and the reſt of the Juſtices at the general Quarter-Seſſions held in</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>for the County of</hi> Berks, <hi>the tenth, eleventh and twelfth day of the Eleventh Month, called</hi> January, 1664.</head>
               <p>The Juſtices being come into the Town, the morning before they ſate, a Paper was ſent (by one of the Priſoners) to them to read; but being refuſed by <hi>W. Armorer,</hi> who would have had it burnt, it was ſent to the Court, and delivered to the Cryer; which <hi>W. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morer</hi> perceiving it, cryed out, Burn it, for it ſhould not be read; and therefore it is thought meet here to be publiſhed: A true Copy of which here followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="paper">
                           <opener>
                              <salute>Friends,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>IT will be a good and precious thing, To have the fear of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eyes, and therein to act in all things towards all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and then you will act in righteouſneſs, and do the thing that is juſt, if in the fear of the Lord you ſtand, and are exerciſed therein in your proceedings; for it is that which makes men honourabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, and in Ages to come to be had in renown by the generation of the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>gh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and the memory of ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>h who in the fear of the Lord do act in their day in Juſtice, and Righteouſneſs, ſhall live for ever, when the Name of the wicked ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ot, and be blotted out from under Heaven, who have had no regard to the fear of God, neither hath Equi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>y and Juſtice have had place in their hearts, and ſuch ſhall eat the fruit of their own doings, and receive a juſt reward from the hands of the Lord, according to their work, in the day when God ſhall judg the ſecrets of all mens hearts, and ſearch out the hidden things of darkneſs, and then ſhall every man be rewarded according to their deeds done in the body, whether they be good, or whether they be evil.</p>
                           <p>Wherefore Friends, the Lord hath put it into my heart to write un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and that I may be clear in his fight, and that the neglect of ſuch a thing may not lye upon my Conſcience as diſobedience, I ſay
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56124:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> unto you, Be conſiderate and ſober in your minds, and calmly and ſeriouſly weigh what you are going about, and let not raſhneſs and envy overſway you, becauſe that the God of Heaven takes notice of your proceedings, and your actions are regiſtred in a Book of Remembrance: But let Juſtice be your Rule, and let the Law of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity be your Guide; let the Light of Jeſus in your hearts and Couſciences, be your Counſellor; becauſe if you ſtart aſide from that, and act not according thereunto, you cannot pleaſe God, nor do the thing that is juſtifiable in his ſight; but you will bring guilt upon your Conſciences, which no man upon the earth ſhall ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit you of; and the ſentence of condemnation you will certainly feel, by the Spirit of the living God, which judgeth righteouſly, without reſpect of perſons: And to lye under that guilt and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence from the Lord in your own hearts and conſciences, will be ſad and heavy indeed; for a wounded conſcience, who can bear? If the Lord wound men inwardly in their conſciences, becauſe of tranſgreſſion againſt his righteous Law of Equity, who can bind them up, or heal them? Will the ſaying, <hi>We have a Law, and by our Law he</hi> (the juſt) <hi>ought to dye, or ſuffer?</hi> Will this eaſe them? Oh no! that will not remove that weight and burden from off their conſciences, which they do bring upon them by acting and walking contrary to the Light or Law of God in their own hearts; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of this, the Lord often brings ſhame and confuſion upon men, and diſhonour and a curſe in all ages hath attended and followed thoſe that have been found in that way of afflicting, troubling, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting and perſecuting innocent and harmleſs people, becauſe of the exerciſe of their Conſcience towards God, and for their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto his requirings. And do ye think to gain honour, if ye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt us in afflicting of us becauſe we cannot tranſgreſs the Royal Law written in our hearts? I tell you no, for we are a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that deſire to ſpend our dayes here in this world, in the fear of God, and to follow him in all things which he doth require of us, to keep his Commandments and his Statutes, and to worſhip him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his mind, in ſpirit and in truth: And this is all we deſire, (which is our right and priviledge, as we are free-born people in this our Native Country) That we may have liberty ſo to do; but if for ſo doing; and nothing elſe, we muſt ſuffer, (as ancient Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have done) we are content, knowing that the Lord will plead
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56124:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> our cauſe, and will care for us; and we cannot deny him to pleaſe men, but muſt ſtill to ourlives end, ſerve and obey him, and wait upon him, and worſhip him in ſpirit and truth, having engaged our hearts ſo to do, in that he hath made known himſelf to us, and by his Eternal Power redeemed us out of the world, and the ſinful ways thereof, and ſhed abroad his love in our hearts; and we are perſwaded, and do know of a truth, That the Lord hath been, and is with us in this his way which we now walk in; and can you in reaſon and equity expect that we ſhould deny that way in which we have found the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ord to ſatisfie and refreſh our ſouls, and to make our hearts glad? Or is it doing as you would be done by? Would you think it right to be perſecuted and afflicted for walking in that way which you are perſwaded in your ſelves you ought to walk in? If not, do you fulfil the Royal Law, which is, To do to others as you would be done unto? Wherefore, conſider betimes, and have not a hand in afflicting of innocent people becauſe of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: But break off your ſins by righteouſneſs, and your iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by ſhewing mercy to the poor in ſpirit, and afflicted people of God, who ſuffer at this day for no other thing, but for keeping the commands of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and for his Worſhip: For what is the matter? Who have we hurt or wronged in any thing, that here is ſuch furious and unchriſtian-like proceedings againſt us? And if our Adverſaries have nothing againſt us, but becauſe of our obedience to the Law and Worſhip of our God, is this ſuch a crime at this day, that honeſt people for ſo doing ſhould be ſo eagerly and violently proceeded againſt, and that ſnares and traps ſhould be laid to catch and enſnare them? Well, the Lord takes notice of theſe things, and he will ariſe for his own Name and Seeds ſake, before whom the Mountains muſt bow and tremble, and the high places of the earth which ſtands in his way, ſhall be removed, and the Lord God will cut his own way thorow them, before whom all Nations are but as the drop of a bucket, and as the ſmall duſt of the ballance, and they that ſtrive againſt him, cannot be bleſſed. And therefore be wiſe and conſiderate ye Rulers of the Earth, leſt ye be found oppoſing of, and ſtriving againſt that Eternal God that gives us all life and breath, and a being here in the world, who will be too ſtrong for you, if you ſhall think in your hearts to ſtop and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his appearance in the hearts of his people, and bind the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56124:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> (in which it is his Right and Prerogative to rule, and no Mans upon the Earth) from following the Lord in what his Light leads and draws it unto, which will be Uſurpation and great ſin charged upon you in the day of the Lord, when you ſhall come before the Throne of his Juſtice and give an account unto him; Wherefore, kiſs the Son, ſtoop and bown unto the Light of God's Son which appears in your hearts, and convinceth you of ſin, leaſt the anger and indignation of the Lord be kindled, and flame and break out like devouring fire, and burn in your own hearts ſo as it can never be quenched.</p>
                           <p>Here are many of us Priſoners in this Gaol, and have been long, (wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ch is not unknown to you) both men and women, and almoſt ſome whole Families, and ſeveral Aged People, many, becauſe we cannot break the Command of our Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt; who hath ſaid unto his Followers, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> becauſe he leads them (and keeps them) out of the ſtrife, and out of ſin and wickedneſs, into Love, Peace and Truth, from which mankind was degenerated, when the ſwearing came in; which was to bind the conſcience, becauſe they were gone, and erred from the love and truth of God, in the heart, which Chriſt our Saviour reſtores into again, and ſays unto ſuch, ſwear not; for truth binds them, and their yea is yea, and their nay is nay; and becauſe we cannot break this Command of Chriſt, we are enſnared, and do ſuffer at this day, and many may be expoſed to utter ruin in this world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thereof, and the guilt of the ruin of innocent people and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, may come upon you, if in a raſh and unchriſtian-like ſpirit ye run on againſt them, (which may be in your power to prevent) the ſufferings and cryes of whom will, enter into the ears of the Lord God of Sabbath, who will hear and have regard thereunto, if men do not regard, and will recompence thoſe that trouble his, into their own boſoms.</p>
                           <p>And others here are that ſuffer for worſhipping God in ſpirit and truth, according to the Scriptures, who cannot forſake the ancient Doctrine and practice of the Apoſtles, who exhorted true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans not to forſake the aſſembling themſelves together; and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but perform that Chriſtian and innocent duty, for which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is ſought againſt us, by ſuch as have given way to that ſpirit of enmity which always appeared againſt the way and worſhip of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56124:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> true God, which ſuch that are joined unto, will feel their reward and portion with; and their inhumane and illegal proceedings may in time be more fully and manifeſtly declared and laid open to the world.</p>
                           <p>Now are theſe things worthy of ſuch ſtrait bonds, and cloſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, even to the endangering the lives of your peaceable Neighbours, who have not done any man wrong; but becauſe of the tenderneſs of their Conſciences towards God, they muſt be thus uſed, ſo that hereby at leaſt their health in the outward man comes to be impaired, by reaſon of keeping in, and being kept from their honeſt Callings and Employments in the Creation; ſo that theſe things tend to the deſtruction of men, women and children, and civil commerce among men, and only becauſe of their faithful obedience to the Lord, in what they are perſwaded in their hearts unto by his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Spirit, and conſtancy in his way, which they can never deny, whatever they ſuffer in this world; neither can any of theſe things (I am perſwaded) ſeperate us (who have truly and experimentally taſted thereof) from the love of God which we feel in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, in whom we have the aſſurance thereof unto our ſouls.</p>
                           <p>Wherefore I ſay, Oh ye men in Power and Authority in the world, Be cool in your minds, and let the cauſe of the Oppreſſed and Afflicted people of God, be pondered by you, and take heed of turning your hand againſt them; for if you do make that your work, To root out and deſtroy them, it will be too hard for you, and your eyes ſhall never ſee the accompliſhment thereof; but if ſome or many of us do ſeal our teſtimony with our deareſt lives and blood, yet will the Lord raiſe up more in the ſame power and ſpirit, to bear witneſs unto his Name in the ſame way in which we ſerve him, and you will be found fighting againſt God, till he be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to anger againſt you, if Juſtice and Mercy be not ſhewed to them; and ye ſhall not obtain mercy and favour at the hand of the Lord; which that you may, is my deſire, who deſires the good and ſalvation of your immortal ſouls, and not your deſtruction, and am a true Friend to Juſtice and Righteouſneſs, and thoſe who are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed therein, and ſuffers with the deſpiſed people of God, for the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Jo: Coale.</signed>
                              <dateline>
                                 <hi>From the Gaol in</hi> Reading, <date>
                                    <hi>the</hi> 16th <hi>of the</hi> 11th <hi>mon:</hi> 1664.</date>
                              </dateline>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56124:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> In the morning, the <hi>11th</hi> day of the month aforeſaid, about fifty Priſoners were called to the Barr, of which were about eight of the Baptized people; an Indictment was read againſt them for wilfully refuſing the Oath at <hi>Abingdon,</hi> the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> &amp;c. To which at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry</hi> they had pleaded not g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lty: The Jury being ſworn, they were going to ſwear <hi>Champion</hi> the Clerk; but <hi>Tho: Curtis</hi> deſired to ſpeak a few words before he took his Oath, being granted, ſaid, <hi>Whereas there was an Indictment read againſt us for refuſing the Oath of Allegiance, when the Oath was never tendered us; for the Statute ſaith it ſhould be tendered upon the Evangeliſts, and it is the opinion of the Judges, That it muſt be read to the party, otherwiſe it cannot be a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful tender; as for inſtance, about thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e years ſince,</hi> Capt. Pecke, <hi>with divers others, being called at an Aſſizes before</hi> Baron Turner <hi>in this place, the Judg asked him whether he would take the Oath of Allegiance; Capt.</hi> Peck <hi>told him he was not committ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d for refuſing that, but was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at a Meeting. The Judg replyed, I do not read it to you, I do but ask you the queſtion; for if I ſhould read it to you, you would be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a</hi> Premunire, &amp;c. <hi>And this is our caſe, We were not committed at firſt for refuſing the Oath of Allegiance, but were taken at a Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and when we expected to have our Trial according to our Mittimus, they asked us whether we would take the Oath, but it was not read to us; for the firſt of us that was called, they were very angry with about his Hat, and never ſo much as asked him whether he would take it. The next that was called, was no</hi> Quaker <hi>ſo called; and he coming before them bowing, with his hat in his hand, they ask<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d him to take it, and he did take it; but then was not I, nor forty more of us called to the Barr, as we can prove by many witneſſes: Another thing is, the Indictment ought to comprehend the whole Oath; but this is falſe in many places.</hi> Then one <hi>Proctor</hi> a Counſellor, and a Juſtice ſo called, being on the Bench, ſtood up, ſaying, As to your being taken at a Meeting, the Court takes no notice of that; you are here indicted for refuſing the Oath of Allegiance, and the Clerk hath ſworn to the Indictment: And wherereas you ſay, the Oath was not read to you, you ſay falſe; for I my ſelf was at <hi>Newberry</hi> Seſſions, and the Oath was read to you there: Then ſeveral of the Priſoners cryed it was falſe, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet read to them: <hi>Proctor</hi> asked whether the Indictment was read? <hi>T. C.</hi> Yes. Then ſaid <hi>Proctor.</hi> The Oath was in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment. <hi>T. C.</hi> That matters not, that was the Indictment, and no
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56124:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> Legal tender of the Oath to us; for we declare in the preſence of God, That the Oath was never read to us; and you do us much wrong; you ought not to deal ſo hardly by us, you ought to help the Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oners at the Barr; inſtead of which you are ſet againſt us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Procter</hi> ſaid, It is for my King and Countrey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jo: Kemboll,</hi> one of the Priſoners, replyed, He did not believe the King did deſire to enrich himſelf with the undoing ſo many poor men and their Families.</p>
               <p>The Judg of the Seſſions, <hi>Edward Dolby,</hi> ſtood up, and asked <hi>William Armorer</hi> again, Whether it was not read to us? Who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Yes.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Tho: Chelton,</hi> one of the Priſoners, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed to him to come off the Bench, being a Witneſs againſt us. Which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did, and ſwore that the Oath was read to them all, and that they were called one by one; and ſo returned on the Bench again, and ſate as one of their Judges.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Champion</hi> the Clerk ſwore alſo to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>But the Priſoners ſtill denyed that it was tendered to them; but were interrupted.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Procter</hi> ſtood up, and ſaid, <hi>You Gentlemen of the Jury, I deſire you to take notice, Here is Sir</hi> William Armorer, <hi>a Perſon of Honour, and Mr.</hi> Champion, <hi>the Clerk of the Peace, have ſworn, That the Oath was read to them all. Now you muſt either bring in theſe men guilty, or elſe you will make theſe two,</hi> (William Armorer <hi>and the Clerk) perjured perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One of the Priſoners, <hi>Richard Billingſly,</hi> ſaid, I am here indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and another with me, for refuſing the Oath of Allegiance the ſame <hi>12th</hi> day of <hi>July,</hi> at <hi>Abingdon,</hi> and I was not called till the <hi>13th</hi> day, after <hi>W. Armorer</hi> was gone out of Town; and yet he and the Clerk have taken their Oaths, That it was there tendered to us all, (they being put in the ſame Indictment) but I was not ſo much as called that day, (as the Reader may ſee by the foregoing Relation.) But they would have waved that.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. C.</hi> deſired the Court would take notice of this thing, That theſe two men were indicted in this Indictment for refuſing the Oath the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> when as they were not called that day at all; and though <hi>W. A.</hi> and the Clerk have ſworn that we were called to the Barr particularly, yet they were not called that day; and <hi>W. A.</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:56124:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> went out of Town early the next morning before the Court ſate, and they were not called in two hours after he was gone, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Indictment was falſe.</p>
               <p>Then the Judg ſaid to <hi>Champion</hi> the Clerk, Did you call theſe men particularly? and did you read the Oath to them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k.</hi> I did call them particularly to the Barr by their Names; and the Oath was read to them, upon which many of the Priſoners cryed out it was falſe, it was falſe.</p>
               <p>But ſaid a Juſtice on the Bench, Were they called before the Oath was read? or was the Oath read firſt, and they called after?</p>
               <p>The Priſoners cryed, That is the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>Then ſaid the Clerk, I muſt ſpeak the truth, I cannot well tell; but the Gaoler gave me a Note of their Names, and I called them particularly: But whether it was read to them before or after they were called, I cannot tell; but if I had thought they had been ſo critical, I would have been more careful.</p>
               <p>A Priſoner ſaid, Take notice of that, Jury.</p>
               <p>So the Jury went forth, and ſtaid not long, but brought them in not guilty.</p>
               <p>So the Cryer demanded money of the Priſoners for the Jury, and the Court broke up, being adjourned till the afternoon, and our Friends departed, being cleared by the Jury; only the Gaoler told ſeveral of them they muſt appear again in the afternoon.</p>
               <p>The Court being ſate again, ſeveral of our Friends appeared; but being informed by ſome, that they intended to inſnare them again, and being cleared by the Jury, they went out of the Court, as judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had no reaſon to ſtay to be enſnared by ſuch as had enmity againſt them, moſt of the moderateſt Juſtices being gone.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Tho: Curtis</hi> and his Wife, <hi>Geo: Lamboll</hi> and his Wife, and three Friends more, being called, they appeared, the reſt being abſent, the Juſtices threatned to fine the Gaoler for thoſe that were want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſaying, Did we not give you Order to ſtay them? Who anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, As ſoon as I heard your Order, I run down the ſtairs upon my faith, but they were gone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. C.</hi> ſaid, I ſuppoſe they would not have gone away, had they known your Order. But being cleared by the Jury, they thought it was ſufficient; and I my ſelf was gone, not intending to come again;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56124:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> but when they told me I was called for, I came again; for I am not aſhamed to ſhew my face, nor afraid of any thing that I have done; and I know <hi>W. Armorer</hi> his man <hi>Venter,</hi> is warrant enough to take me at any time.</p>
               <p>Judg. <hi>Though the Jury did clear you of that Indictment, yet they could not clear you of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the Clerk reading over their Names, they called for <hi>Thomas Heifield.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. C.</hi> ſaid, That is a man that hath ſerved the King faithfully, and hath many cuts in his head, and wounds about his body, that he received in the Kings Army, yet he is regarded no more then others, though he fought and ventured his life for the King; and being come now to make conſcience of an Oath, muſt be enſnared with the Oath of Allegiance.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>A. Curtis</hi> was called.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. C.</hi> anſwered, Here is ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her whoſe Father laid down his life, and ſuffered death for the ſervice of the King; yet ſhe alſo muſt be enſnared with the Oath.</p>
               <p>Then they called for the Statute-Book.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. C.</hi> ſaid, We ſee your ſnare well enough; it is not the part of men of Honour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſeek to enſnare thoſe whom the Jury hath cleared; but theſe things will appear as a blot in your Scutcheon: We do believe you aim to enſnare us, and it is our Eſtates you ſeek after, and it is well if ſome of you have not begg'd them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Procter</hi> the Councellor ſtood up in great rage, and bid the Clerk read the Oath to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. C.</hi> ſaid, Be not ſo haſty, for thou didſt but a little time ſince, charge theſe two men (pointing to <hi>William Armorer</hi> and the Clerk) with being perjured; for thou toldſt the Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, That either they muſt bring us in guilty, or elſe theſe men were perjured; and the Jury brought us in not guilty. And thou need'ſt not be ſo fierce now, for the time was, when thou waſt as fierce in <hi>O. Cromwell</hi>'s dayes.</p>
               <p>Then the Judg bid the Clerk read the Oath; being done, asked <hi>T. C.</hi> if he heard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t; who anſwered yes. So they held the Bible to him.</p>
               <p>He told them he could read them a better Leſſon in that Book, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f they would hear, having the Book in his hand. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey bid him ſay
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56124:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> after the Clerk, who read the Oath; which he did till he came to that clauſe, <hi>And I do ſwear, &amp;c.</hi> Then he ſaid, But I do not, for I cannot ſwear; but what I have ſaid, I do helieve, and queſtion not but I ſhall prove as good a Subject to the King, as ſome of you. So they bid the Gaoler take him away.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Geo: Lamboll</hi> was called: They asked him whether he would take the Oath of Allegiance?</p>
               <p>Who anſwered, As to the Oath of Obedience he could promiſe very much, and he ſhould keep his promiſe, though ſome did repute us as lyars.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Sarah</hi> his Wife was called to the Barr: They asked her if ſhe would take the Oath?</p>
               <p>She anſwered, At preſent ſhe was not ſatisfied that ſhe might ſafely do it, or to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>And the other three Friends, <hi>Tho: Tudway, John Paine,</hi> and <hi>James Marlow</hi> being called, they asked them the ſame queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. Tudway</hi> asked, Whether it was better to obey Chriſt, then them?</p>
               <p>They ſaid, That was not the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>He told them he could not ſwear. The others anſwering to the ſame purpoſe, they were taken away.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>A. Curtis</hi> was called to the Barr: One of the Juſtices ſaid, <hi>Come</hi> Nan, <hi>I know you will take it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. C.</hi> Yes, if thee or any one could convince me that I might lawfully do it, and not break Chriſts command, who hath ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> And being asked the ſame queſtion often, anſwered to the ſame purpoſe as before.</p>
               <p>One of the Juſtices ſaid, <hi>But the Apoſtle ſaid, That an Oath for confirmation endeth ſtrife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She anſwered, That Chriſt the everlaſting Oath of God, who puts an end to ſtriſe, him I know ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Armorer</hi> being on the Bench, ſaid, <hi>This is the old tone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. C.</hi> It was before thee waſt, and will he when thou haſt no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>They ſtill continuing to ask her if ſhe would take it; anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Yes, if any one could make it appear that I might lawfully do it, and not break my peace with God in my Conſcience.</p>
               <p>But they asked her again, and bid her anſwer if ſhe would take it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56124:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> or not. Who replyed, I ſhall give no other anſwer. So the Gaoler took her away.</p>
               <p>The ſame day at night, <hi>Tho: Tudway</hi> one of the Priſoners, living in the ſame Town, having been to ſee his Wife and Children, as he was going to Gaol again, overtook <hi>William Armorer,</hi> and having paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, he called, and ſent his man, and ſtayed him, and asked him why he did run away from the Seſſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. T.</hi> ſaid, I did not, but am going to Gaol, for I am a Priſoner, and thou haſt nothing to do with us, for we are the Gaolers Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and we were all at the Seſſions, and that was ſufficient; and ſaid it was hard meaſure that he might not go ſee his Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>Juſtice <hi>Brown</hi> being preſent, ſaid it was; <hi>but you muſt be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the Laws.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>W. A.</hi> ſaid, <hi>You muſt take the Oath; an Oath for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion endeth ſtrife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. T.</hi> ſaid, But I am not in ſtrife; for I can ſay, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou haſt kept me this forty weeks unjuſtly in Priſon, the Lord forgive thee; and thou waſt beſt have a care what thou doſt to us, for thou muſt give an account for thy bad deeds.</p>
               <p>W. A. ſaid, <hi>You ſhall ſee at the day of Judgment, whoſe arſe will be blackeſt, yours, or mine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Priſoner ſaid, Thoſe words doth not become a Juſtices mouth. So he ſent him to the Gaol.</p>
               <p>The next day, being the <hi>12th</hi> day of the month, the other ſix Friends, viz. <hi>Joſeph Coale, Rob: Pecock, Benj: Coale, William Yeet, Rich: Green,</hi> and <hi>Jo: Tray,</hi> were called to the Barr, and <hi>Tho: Bartlet</hi> alſo, who was freed by the Jury the day before. The Clerk having read the Oath of Allegiance, the Judg ſaid, <hi>Joſeph Coale, What ſay you, will you take the Oath of Allegiance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. Coale</hi> ſaid, I have ſomething to ſay to the Court, and deſire I may be heard—was interrupted by <hi>Procter,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Will you take the Oath, and you ſhall be heard?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> C.</hi> I have ſomething firſt to ſpeak concerning my taking up, and commitment; for I was in my Friend, <hi>Tho: Curtis</hi> his houſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not well, and <hi>W. Armorer</hi> pickt a lock to come to me, and pull'd me out of my Chamber—was interrupted by <hi>W.</hi> A. who called him Rogue, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon which one on the Bench pull'd him to be quiet.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:56124:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> One of the Priſoners ſaid, Thoſe words did not become a Juſtice on the Bench.</p>
               <p>Judg. <hi>Well, what ſay you, will you take the Oath, or not? we will not hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you of ſuch things now.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. Coale</hi> ſaid, Why, are you aſhamed to hear of picking the Lock, and ſuch illegal proceedings? You ought to hear and do Juſtice, as you are Magiſtrates, and not to hide and cover ſuch things—was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted.</p>
               <p>Judg <hi>Give him the Book, will you ſwear or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. C.</hi> I would have ſpoken of my taking up, and known for what I have been kept in Priſon all this time; but ſeeing I cannot be heard, I ſhall ſpeak as to the Oath. Indeed I have not been uſed to ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but if you can ſatisfie my Conſcience that I may lawfully ſwear, and not break the command of Chriſt my Saviour, I may take this Oath: The Book being given him, he was turning to the fifth of <hi>James;</hi> and W. A. cryed, Oh, he is going to the fifth of <hi>Matthew;</hi> and called the Gaoler to take him away.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>R. Pocock</hi> was called.</p>
               <p>Judg. <hi>What ſay you, will you take the Oath of Allegiance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R. Pocock.</hi> I deſire to ſpeak ſomething concerning the manner of my commitment—but was interrupted by the Clerk, who ſaid, he ſhould anſwer firſt whether he would take the Oath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R. P.</hi> Thou art not Judg of the Seſſions, therefore hold thy peace.</p>
               <p>Juſtices. <hi>Will you take the Oath of Allegiance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R. P.</hi> I deſire to know whether it be in love to the King, or to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare me, that it is tendered to me? For when I was committed to Priſon by <hi>W. Armorer,</hi> and <hi>Tho: Seikes</hi> Mayor, <hi>W.</hi> A. ſaid he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve I was a peaceable man.</p>
               <p>W. A. ſaid, <hi>I do believe ſo ſtill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R. P.</hi> If my word may be taken inſtead of ſwearing, I can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to be true to the King; and if I break my promiſe, let the ſame puniſhment be inflicted upon me, as on them who break their Oaths.</p>
               <p>So the Gaoler took him away, and <hi>Benjamin Coale</hi> was called.</p>
               <p>Judg. <hi>What ſay you,</hi> Benjamin Coale, <hi>will you take this Oath that was read to you?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:56124:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>B. Coale</hi> ſaid, Was it read to me? I did not underſtand it, for I am but a young Lad, and unacquainted with theſe things?</p>
               <p>Judg. <hi>Shall we read it again to you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>B. C.</hi> I ſuppoſe that I am a Priſoner; and was I brought here to have Juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce? or to be enſnared? I deſire the Court would hear me a few words concerning my commitment at firſt, which was not upon this account; but I was firſt committed upon the account of the new Act, and I have been informed, That thoſe that are taken upon that account, ought not to be enſnared by any other.</p>
               <p>Judg. <hi>Well, that is nothing; will you take the Oath, or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>B. C.</hi> I deſire to know for what I have be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this long time a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner?</p>
               <p>Judg. <hi>We take no notice of your being a P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r; you are here; will you take the Oath? give him the Book:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>B. C.</hi> Do you own this Book? (having it in his hand) at which they were offended, and cryed, Take him away, he deſerves to be whipt.</p>
               <p>But he deſired the Court to take notice, That he did not refuſe the Oath; but if they could prove by the Script<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res, that it was lawful to ſwear, he would ſwear.</p>
               <p>Then the Gaoler took him away; and <hi>William <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eet</hi> was called.</p>
               <p>Judg. <hi>William Yeet, what ſay you? will you ſwear?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. T.</hi> The day of the Lord is come; therefore I rather chuſe to obey God, then man.</p>
               <p>Judg. ſaid, <hi>It is enough.</hi> And <hi>Richard Green</hi> was called.</p>
               <p>Clerk ſaid, <hi>Will you take the Oath?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R. Green.</hi> I deſire to know for what I have lain half a year in priſon? (He being taken out of his Shop, being a poor man, and having a Wife and Family to maintain by his labour.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. Armorer</hi> anſwered, <hi>For refuſing to take the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ante.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R G.</hi> I fear you do not know what an Oath is.</p>
               <p>Some of them ſaid they would make him know what it is, asking him again if he would take it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R. G.</hi> ſaid, If you can convince me that I may do it, and not break the command of God, I will take it.</p>
               <p>W. Arm. <hi>It is written in the Scripture, That an Oath is the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:56124:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>R. G.</hi> ſaid, Chriſt is the Oath of God; and to witneſs Chriſt in me, is the confirmation of the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h; and he commands me not to ſwear at all.</p>
               <p>Judg. <hi>Will you take this Oath, or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R. G.</hi> I cannot ſwear, but do not deny Allegiance to the King.</p>
               <p>So the Gaoler took him away, and <hi>John Tray</hi> was called; and they aked him the ſame queſtion as the former; who anſwered, That he could not ſwear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then <hi>Tho: Bartlet</hi> was called; they asked him if he would ſwear.</p>
               <p>He anſwered, He had learned better then to ſwear.</p>
               <p>The Clerk bid the Cryer give him the Book; and he would have read in the Book.</p>
               <p>But they ſaid, He muſt ſwear.</p>
               <p>He anſwered as before, he had learned better.</p>
               <p>Now when this <hi>Tho: Bartlet</hi> was taken at the Meeting, <hi>W. Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> accuſed him of Plotting and Rebelling againſt the King; but when he had got him in another ſnare, that was no more mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and ſaid he made breach upon breach upon the Kings Laws, becauſe he did not put off his hat when he was brought before him, and that he workt on holy days; ſtamping his ſtick on the ground, ſaid, <hi>By his troth he ſhould go to New-England for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now we come to the proceedings at the ſame Seſſions, the ſame <hi>12th</hi> day of the <hi>11th</hi> Month, againſt four others of our Friends, viz. <hi>Chriſtopher Cheeſeman, Anne Sharp, Bridget Smith,</hi> and <hi>Margery Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardſon,</hi> who were taken at a Meeting, and committed upon the third ſuppoſed offence.</p>
               <p>Being brought to the Town-Hall, expecting to hear their Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, they were not called, nor ſuffered to come in the hearing of the Court, but kept at the lower end of the Hall ſeveral hours, the Juſtices having little to do, but the trial of theſe four perſons, it being the third day of their ſitting, and moſt of the Juſtices being gone; and having kept the Priſoners ſeveral hours, they ſent them to priſon again, and the Court adjourned till the ſecond hour in the afternoon, the Grand Jury being gone out, waiting for the Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſome hours, which were <hi>John Venter, W. Armorer</hi> his man, and <hi>Rich: Grover</hi> his Clerk, <hi>Hugh Smith, Daniel Seamer</hi> and his Son; which Witneſſes being ſworn, were very much different in their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56124:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> Ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dence, ſome ſaying they ſaw them at the Meeting, but heard them ſay nothing, nor do nothing, but only that they were there.</p>
               <p>The Court being ſate, the Cryer called for the Grand Inqueſt, who appeared, and brought in their Verdict <hi>Ignoramus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon which <hi>W A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> roſe up from his ſeat in great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I will come off the Bench, and ſwea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> againſt them, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> my Oath, That I have found</hi> Chriſt: Cheeſeman <hi>twenty times at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and when I came, he would tell me there was not my numb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>: So I was fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n to wipe my noſe,</hi> (wiping his finger then on his Noſe) <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd return back like a Coxc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mb as I went; and thus I have been p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> with him: and I will take my Oath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t when I have ask<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d them ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t they did at the meeting, they have told me to wait up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd, and to ſeek God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, If that can be proved that they have co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>feſſed they were there to ſeek or wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, it is enough; and would have encouraged the Jury of fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Bills up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n it.</p>
               <p>Oh abominable, unheard of w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ckedneſs and cruelty, that to wait upon, or ſeek God, ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld be accounted ſuch a crime, as to deſerve no leſs puniſhment then ſeven years baniſhment or death it ſelf!</p>
               <p>Well, but <hi>W. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> his man <hi>Vent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> being called<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and beginning to ſpeak, his Maſter, <hi>W.</hi> A. ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to him, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ck, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>membe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the</hi> 23d <hi>day of the Month?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s man anſwered, 'Tis no matter for the day of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, I know the time well enough.</p>
               <p>Upon which a ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>der by ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, A <hi>Rogue, do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he day of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nth. He deſerves to be kickt out of the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t:</hi> And the people fell out into great laughter.</p>
               <p>And ſo the Jury went forth the ſecond time: the Jury ſtill ſcrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the buſineſs, could not agree to find the Bills.</p>
               <p>And <hi>W. Armo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> off the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch in grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rage, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d took h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Cath, and then went into the Council Chamber to info<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m the Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y: So t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at there wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Judg, <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ward D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Juſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>(P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r)</hi> left on the bench<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>W. Armorer</hi> being ſword as a W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tneſs; and whether they two could ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a Seſſions, neither of them being of the <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>um;</hi> no doubt but they can tell.</p>
               <p>Well; notw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thſtanding the Jury returned the ſecond time, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d brought in <hi>Ignora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:56124:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> Upon which <hi>Procter</hi> began to be very angry, ſaying to the Jury, <hi>Would you do ſo, having ſuch Evidence, and Sir</hi> William Armorer <hi>an honourable Gentleman, having taken his Oath alſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Jury anſwered, 'Twas true, Sir <hi>W.</hi> A. was an honourable Gentleman, but was a man ſubject to paſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Procter</hi> replyed, ſaying, <hi>If he were, it did not become them to tell him ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then <hi>W. Armorer</hi> preſt the Judg to have them fined ten pounds a man.</p>
               <p>The Judg anſwered, No, if that were their judgment, between God and their own Conſcienees be it.</p>
               <p>But W. A. preſt to have them bound to their good behaviour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had ſome ſcruples concerning his ſwearing, being as they ſaid, tender in conſcience touching ſo dubious a matter, and did que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether they might take his oath or not; for it may be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that <hi>Procter</hi> himſelf but the day before did tell the Jury, that if they did not bring in the Priſoners guilty, they would make W. A. and the Clerk perjured perſons; and the Jury did not bring in the Priſoners guilty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the Priſoners being cleared by the Jury, the two Juſtice on the Bench, and <hi>W. Armorer</hi> not being pleaſed with it, committed them to the Gaol again as factious perſons, till they ſhould pay their fees. So the Seſſions ended.</p>
               <p>And the next day, being the <hi>13th</hi> day of the Month, W. A ſent for the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Priſoners before mentioned, to his houſe, where three of them were brought by the Gaoler; but one of them being an ancient weakly woman, having taken cold the day before, by reaſon of their being kept ſo long at the Seſſions, it being very cold wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not being well, was left behind: Which when W. A. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, he began to be very angry, and bid the Gaoler fetch her, though on Horſe-back.</p>
               <p>So the Gaoler fetcht her alſo, and having kept them about two hours, being very cold weather, nothing was ſaid to them, but were returned back again to priſon.</p>
               <p>The <hi>16th</hi> day of the ſame month, they were had before him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to his Houſe, where was alſo <hi>Tho: Kenton</hi> Mayor W. A. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Grover</hi> his Clerk to read the Oath of Allegiance to them; which being done, told them if they would take it, they ſhould have their liberty.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:56124:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> They anſwered; that they were Priſoners by an Order of Soſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, till they would pay their Fees, and therefore would not anſwer to any ſuch queſtions until they were at liberty.</p>
               <p>And after ſome diſcourſe, they were committed again for refuſing the Oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the <hi>28th</hi> of the <hi>12th</hi> month called <hi>February,—</hi>64, they were ſent for again before <hi>W. Armorer,</hi> who told them they were as they were before, if they would pay their fees, they ſhould have their liberty.</p>
               <p>So when they came out of his houſe, the Gaoler bid them go to their own homes.</p>
               <p>And whether theſe proceedings be according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw, or mens wills, the Reader may judg; but we are ſure the innocent ſuffers.</p>
               <p>The 22<hi>d</hi> of the <hi>11th</hi> Month called <hi>January,—</hi>64, <hi>W. Armorer</hi> came to the Meeting, and took <hi>Joan Willeſby<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mary Winter,</hi> and <hi>Mary Richardſon,</hi> and ſent them to the houſe of Correction for three dayes, upon the ſecond offence, as he calls it. And there being ſix men more, viz. <hi>William Lamboll, William Tompſon, Leo: Key<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Sadler, Tho: Speed,</hi> and <hi>John Boult,</hi> he pull'd one of them down by violence from his ſeat, and ſent for the Gaoler, whoſe ſervant came, whom W. A. commanded to take them to priſon, which was done by his man <hi>Venter,</hi> and the Gaolers man, who haled them to the Gaol without Warrant or Mittimus.</p>
               <p>The next day he ſent for the ſix men to his houſe, where he, with <hi>Tho: Kenton</hi> the Mayor, asked them if they would ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Oath of Allegiance; and called to <hi>Grover</hi> his Clerk to read it.</p>
               <p>One of the Friends, <hi>W. Lamboll,</hi> asked, to what end do you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire me to ſwear?</p>
               <p>W. A. ſaid, <hi>To be true to the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſwearing Allegiance ſufficient, though I do it not?</p>
               <p>W. A. ſaid, <hi>No you muſt do it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> ſaid, It ſeems doing Allegiance is the thing that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired?</p>
               <p>He anſwered, <hi>Yes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> I own Allegiance to the King, and am willing to do all his juſt and lawful requirings, as a Subject, in things pertaining to this world, and will promiſe thereunto.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:56124:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>W. Armo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, You muſt ſwear to bind you, for if you break your Oath you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e damn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. I.</hi> Will not the breaking of my promiſe be matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to me?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W A.</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſwered, <hi>No,</hi> or to that effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> ſaid, The Scripture ſaith, that no Lyar ſhall enter into the Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gdom of God; and the Devil ſhall receive damnation for lying.</p>
               <p>But ſtill he asked me to ſwear?</p>
               <p>I told him that Chriſt and the Apoſtles forbid ſwearing; and the ſucceeding Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tians denyed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſwear, as <hi>Polycarpus</hi> and others: And ſwearing upon a Book was ſet up by the Antichr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtian Power; and <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtinian</hi> the Emperor was the firſt Inſtitutor of it, as I read of; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dd nothing to the King, for me to kiſs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Book; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will it do him any good: And therefore why ſhould it be put ſo much upon me, ſeeing I will do Allegiance?</p>
               <p>W. A ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d he co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld not help it; and bid the Gaoler take him away if he would not ſwear; and ſaid he might go a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arliament that ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the Law; and he was ſworn to execute the Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aws.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. Lamboll</hi> asked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im why he would put ſuch Laws in execution, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch he could not defend by the Scriptures nor right reaſon?</p>
               <p>Then he bid the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aoler take him away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. L.</hi> ſaid, The Lord God everlaſting, (in whoſe preſence I am juſtified in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s thing, and before whoſe Judgment-ſeat we muſt all appear) knoweth my heart, that I do not deny to ſwear out of ſtubbornneſs, nor out of obſtiracy, or denying Alleg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance to the Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g; but only and alone for Conſcience ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke towards God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt Jeſus (whom we are to hear in all things) ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Oath be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng read to <hi>William Tompſon,</hi> and the Book held to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, ſaid, Alas, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s all that ye can do, ſo often to tender us this Oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h to inſnare us? And that he did own what was read, and could promiſe the things contained in the Oath.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Cler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> havi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ven him the Book he ſaid, Out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Book can I pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat it is not lawful to ſwear at all.</p>
               <p>W. A. ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, <hi>That is in you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> communication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. T.</hi> Nay it is not at all, which are Chriſts words to them that were followers of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, <hi>I ſay unto you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Swear not at all,</hi> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56124:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> all ſwearing; <hi>but let your yea be yea, and your nay nay; for whatſoever is more, cometh of evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. A.</hi> began to be angry with him, becauſe he did not anſwer whether he would, or would not ſwear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. T.</hi> I can promiſe the things contained in the Oath, and is not that ſufficient?</p>
               <p>Mayor ſaid, <hi>That doth not anſwer the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. T.</hi> If I do that which the Law requires, or the ſubſtance of the Oath, it will not be accepted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W.</hi> A. being peeviſh and angry, thruſt him going, he crying for Juſtice, W. A. told him he ſhould have it done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. T.</hi> appealing to the Mayor for Juſtice, he ſaid, <hi>William, I am in place to do the Kings buſineſs, and to execute his Laws, and I muſt do it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. T.</hi> ſaid, But thou muſt have an eye to the Law of God in it.</p>
               <p>The Book being held to <hi>Tho: Speed,</hi> he ſaid, I chuſe rather to obey that Chriſt which you profeſs, who ſaid, <hi>Swear not all,</hi> then you who ſay ſwear.</p>
               <p>W. A. <hi>VVill you? that's enough, take him away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T. S.</hi> Is this thy Juſtice, to command me to be taken away to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for ſaying, I chuſe rather to obey Chriſt then thee?</p>
               <p>Then they asked <hi>John Boult</hi> if he would take the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance?</p>
               <p>Who anſwered, As for my part I am a man that makes conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of my ways, and I have great cauſe to reſpect the Lord, and to eye his way and truth; and as he hath made it known in me, I ſhall in that truth follow him in his holy way; and that which he hath made known to me to be evil, that I dare not do, leſt I ſhould break my peace with my God, which I cannot do for all the world.</p>
               <p>W. A. <hi>You cannot take it, can you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. B.</hi> I cannot go againſt my Conſcience, nor do that which the Lord hath made known to me to be evil.</p>
               <p>W. A. ſaid, <hi>VVhere did you learn that, out of your nail?</hi> (the Friend being a Shoomaker by Trade.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. B.</hi> reproving of him for his jeer, ſaid, Nay, the Lord hath made it known unto me.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:56124:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> Some other diſcourſe paſſed between them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which for brevities ſake we have omitted; and the other two alſo had ſome diſcourſe to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>12th</hi> of the firſt Month called <hi>March,</hi> 1665, <hi>VVilliam Armorer</hi> came again to the Meeting and ſent for the Gaoler, who being come, he ſent <hi>Leonard Coale, James Lavell</hi> and <hi>VValter E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merton</hi> to the Gaol without either Warrant or Mittimus. And at the ſame Meeting took <hi>Chriſtopher Page, Henry Adams, Anne Sharp, Margaret VVhiteheart, Anne Godard, Ann VVeeden, Eli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Lavell</hi> the younger, and <hi>Mary Mathew,</hi> and ſent them to the Counter, and then went into the houſe of <hi>Tho: Curtis,</hi> and puld out his Man-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Henry G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſs,</hi> and put him into the Meeting-Room, and ſaid he run away out of the Meetin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (though the man was never at our Meeting all his life-time, as we heard of) and ſo ſent him to Gaol, and at night he ſent for them all to his houſe, where was Juſtice <hi>Dolby</hi> alſo; and tendered the Oath of Allegance to <hi>L. Coale, J. Lavell</hi> and <hi>VV. Emerton,</hi> and committed them to the Gaol, and told <hi>Henry Groſs Tho: Curtis</hi> his man, that he was miſtaken in him, and let him go again, the reſt he ſent to the Gaol for three days, except A. <hi>Sharp,</hi> who was committed upon the third Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
               <p>The ſecond of the ſecond Month called <hi>Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il,</hi> 1665, came <hi>VV. Armorer,</hi> and <hi>Edw: D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lby</hi> to the Meeting, and took <hi>Chriſto: Cheeſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Hannah VVebb, Anne Harriſon, Eliz: Tudway, Eliz: Dee</hi> the younger, <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>othy Clarke, Hannah Kent;</hi> and <hi>Hannah Lomboll;</hi> and being brought to his houſe by the Conſtable, <hi>Samuel Houſe,</hi> he exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined <hi>H. Lamboll</hi> and <hi>H. Kent,</hi> about their age, and being little, let them go; and ſent the other five to the Gaol for three dayes, and <hi>Chriſto: Cheeſeman</hi> upon the third offence.</p>
               <p>The fourth of the ſecond Month called <hi>April,</hi> the Seſſions for the County of <hi>Berks</hi> was held at <hi>Newberry,</hi> to which place the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to whom the Oath of Allegiance had been tendered, were brought, viz. <hi>Tho: Curtis,</hi> and <hi>Anne</hi> his Wife, <hi>George Lamboll,</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> his Wife, <hi>Tho: Tudway, John Paine, James Marlow, Joſeph Coale, Rob: Pocock, Benjamin Coale, VVilliam Yeet, John Tray, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Green, Thomas Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tlet, VVilliam Lamboll, VVilliam Tompſon, Leo: Key, Anthony Sadler, John Boult, Tho: Speed, Leo: Coale, James Lavel,</hi> and <hi>VValter Eme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ton;</hi> and being brought into the Court,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56124:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> were called to the Barr, and the Oath was read to them, and the Court asked whether they would take the Oath of Allegiance?</p>
               <p>To which they generally anſwered, That for Conſcience-ſake, becauſe Chriſt had commanded not to ſwear at all, they could not do it: but did offer to give under their hands, and promiſe that they would be true to the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And one Friend, <hi>Geo: Lamboll,</hi> being permitted to ſpeak a few words, ſaid to the Court, That the Law by which they proceeded againſt us, was never made againſt a people that feared an Oath, and could not ſwear at all in any caſe; but it was made againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, who denyed Allegiance to the King, and choſe rather to bear the penalty; for they owned Allegiance to another Power, which we deny, and have often declared it; and do offer and promiſe Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to the King, and to no other Power on earth, whilſt we live under Him; and would be willing to undergo the puniſhment of perjured men, if we break our Promiſe.</p>
               <p>So they were put by, and committed to the Aſſizes, the Juſtices ſaying it was a thing too weighty for them: So they would leave them to the Judges.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Anne Curtis</hi> and <hi>Sarah Lamboll</hi> were called.</p>
               <p>They asked <hi>A. Curtis</hi> if ſhe would take the Oath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. C.</hi> ſaid, I look on it as a very hard thing that I ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to take this Oath, being under covert, and my Husband be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here a preſent Sufferer for the very ſame thing; for there is no woman in <hi>England</hi> that I have heard of, under covert, that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to take that Oath, and kept in priſon on that account, except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf and <hi>Sarah Lamboll.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So after more diſcourſe, they put her out of the Court, and bid her take <hi>Sarah Lamboll</hi> with her.</p>
               <p>And upon <hi>A. C.</hi> her ſpeaking a few words to the Juſtices, <hi>W. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morer</hi> ſaid, <hi>Hold your tongue,</hi> Nan, <hi>and turn your back.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And others of the Juſtices ſaid, <hi>Go your wayes, Mrs.</hi> Curtis, <hi>out of the Court, and take Mrs.</hi> Lamboll <hi>with you;</hi> by which they, and many of the Spectators, did judg they ſhould have had their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
               <p>But after they were gone, <hi>W. Armorer</hi> (as ſome of the people ſaid) began to incenſe the Juſtices againſt <hi>A. Curtis,</hi> telling them what a dangerous perſon ſhe was to be ſet at liberty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:56124:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> So they ordered, that <hi>A. Curtis</hi> and <hi>S. Lamboll,</hi> ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Gaol as dangerous and ſuſpicious perſons, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main until the next Aſſize.</p>
               <p>The next day, being the fifth of the Month, two more of our Friends, viz. <hi>Chriſtopher Cheeſeman,</hi> and <hi>Anne Sharp</hi> were called, and two Witneſſes called, viz. a <hi>Daniel Seamer,</hi> and <hi>W. Armorer</hi> his Coach-man; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>a</hi> This <hi>D. Seamer</hi> was ſo drunk the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that he abuſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the Priſoners, ſaying, <hi>he hated them a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> he hated the Devil.</hi>
                  </note> who being ignorant which hand to lay on the Book, his Maſter called to him, ſaying, <hi>Lay on the other hand,</hi> Dick: and being ſworn, were ſent out to the Grand Jury, who having heard their Evidence; returned into the Court, and their Verdict was, <hi>They could not find any ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient proof to find the Priſoners guilty according to the late Act made againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful and Seditious Meetings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At which Verdict <hi>W. Armorer</hi> (according to his uſual manner, if the Jury did not do as he would have them) fell into a great rage, and began to threaten ſome of the Jury that they ſhould be fined; and cauſed them to return again, farther to adviſe in the caſe.</p>
               <p>But being retutned again, their Verdict was as before, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſound reaſons and arguments wherefore they could not find the Bill.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Juſtices put them to the pole, asking them one by one, <hi>Do you find the Bill? &amp;c.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Jury (like men <note n="b" place="margin">For when one would be as a Witneſs that the Priſoners ſaid they were at the Meeting to wait upon God, one of the Iury anſwered, <hi>Wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God? who ſhould they wait upon elſe? ſhould they wait upon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil?</hi>
                  </note>.) ſtood to their judgment, crying, <hi>No, no,</hi> all except five of Nineteen; which five alſo did confeſs it was againſt their Conſciences to find it. Yet the Juſtices <hi>(William Armo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> being ſtill on the Bench) cryed out, <hi>Tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r them the Oath of Allegiance.</hi> To which the Jury as one man, cryed out, they would take it. But when the Juſtices ſaw them ſo ready to take it, they paſt it by.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W.</hi> A. not being pleaſed with theſe proceedings, began to accuſe the <hi>Quake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> in venting moſt audacious and damnable lyes, ſaying in the face of the Country, No body ſhould ever catch them ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or praying, for they ſet boyes at the corners of the ſtreets, to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56124:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> watch, ſo that if an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come to take them, they might have notice thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Which being ſo notoriouſly falſe, no doubt the Country would give as little heed to it, as there was truth in it; and ſo we leave it. For we dare appeal to all people both in this Town, (where our Meetings are known, being publike this eleven or twelve years) and in Country, whether our harmleſs and innocent practiſes, eſpecially in the Service and Worſhip of the true and living God, hath not been of more Chriſtian courage, then to ſet boyes to watch if any body came to ſee us: No, no, we are far from that; for our Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in preaching and publiſhing God enduring truth, and our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſo good effect and acceptance with the Lord, that we are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſhamed nor afraid of any that ſhall come among us; and our daily practice, and his continual frequenting our peaceable Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again and again, (as the Reader may obſerve) doth ſufficiently manifeſt the contrary.</p>
               <p>Well, but to return: the Jury being very much threatned, and much ſtir becauſe the Bill was not found againſt the Priſoners, there was ſome hurry in the Court; but the Priſoners had their liberty, and the Seſſions ended.</p>
               <p>Again, the 23<hi>d</hi> of the ſame Month, <hi>W. Armorer</hi> came to the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, there being not five of the age of ſixteen years, though ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral under age, with his Son and Servant, haled them out, and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Cheeſeman</hi> being there, be bid one of them cudgel <hi>Cheeſeman</hi> out of the room; and as he was going forth, <hi>W.</hi> A. himſelf thruſt at him with his Cane or Staff, and run it between his lips and teeth, there being not his number as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Moreover, W. A. meeting <hi>Chriſtopher Cheeſman</hi> another time in the ſtreet, laid violent hands on him, and pluckt him by the Noſe, and threatned if he catcht him at the Meeting again, he would cut off his Noſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>30th</hi> of the ſame Month, <hi>W.</hi> A. came again to the Meeting, and ſent for <hi>Tho: Kenton</hi> Mayor, who being come, they took <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Cheeſeman, Anne Sharp, Sarah Binfield, Mary Coale, Grace Hutchins, Hannah Lamboll, John Kent, Tho: Conicke,</hi> and <hi>Hannah Wrenn.</hi> and being had to the Houſe of <hi>Giles Pocock,</hi> and having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted together, they ſent <hi>Chriſtopher Cheeſeman,</hi> A. <hi>Sharp,</hi> and <hi>Sarah Binfield,</hi> to the Gaol on the third account.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:56124:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>W. Armorer</hi> ſtill breathing out fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe accuſations againſt them, that they carried Letters about the Country, and then met on that day to plot and contrive inſurrections.</p>
               <p>One of the Friends denying it, told him, if he could prove any ſuch thing, they would be contented to ſuffer whatſoever the Law had provided in that caſe.</p>
               <p>W. A. replyed, <hi>We will make you prove the contrary:</hi> and told them of black ſtrings and ribbons to tye about their arms, and ſuch ſtories which are incredible to any man of gravity and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and yet telling of it with ſuch confidence, as if the man had been an eye-witneſs of that which was never to be ſeen: And one of the Priſoners counſelling him to take heed what he did, for there would come a day wherein he muſt give an account for what he did: W. A. replyed, <hi>We ſhall know at the day of Judgment, whoſe arſe is black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, yours or ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Priſoner told him it was an uncivil thing for one called a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to ſpeak ſuch words.</p>
               <p>He replyed again, <hi>VVhy Sirrah, what incivility is it? is not your noſe your noſe, and your arſe your noſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So they committed <hi>Grace Hutchins</hi> for ſix months to the Gaol, and the reſt for three months; the Mayor being the chief Inſtrument at that time, of their being committed for ſo long time, ſaying, <hi>VVe will not be troubled with them ſo often;</hi> it being in the Summet time, when many were thronged up together. After which, one of the Priſoners ſent him a Letter, a true Copy whereof, here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:56124:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>To</hi> THOMAS KENTON, <hi>Mayor of</hi> Reading, <hi>Theſe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Tho: Kenton:</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>FRiend, Thou art now in a place of Authority in this Town; and as chief Magiſtrate therein, thou haſt power put into thy hand to puniſh evil-doers, and to favour, encourage and protect peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in well-doing; which is the End of outward Rule and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in this world, which was never ordained of God to limi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, ſtop or bind the Conſciences of people to, or from any way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or practiſes of Religion; but it was ordained of God to pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh the evil-doers, and to keep and preſerve men in peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs one with another, that they hurt not, nor wrong not one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor abuſe themſelves nor one another; but that they might be kept in good order one with another in all things outwardly, and not to rule over the conſcience; but he, even God alone, is to rule in the conſcience, and to perſwade it by his Light therein, to, and in his own way and wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p, and therein man is not to meddle, but to leave it free: And he that rules thus, he rules for God, and bears not the Sword in vain, which is to ſtop, limit and bind wickedneſs, and he abuſes not the Power, nor will not turn his Sword (nor Power) againſt ſuch as do well, and follows peace and holineſs, and fears and ſerves the Lord, but will encourage, and be a praiſe unto ſuch who do live peaceably and honeſtly among men; and though ſuch may be falſly accuſed and reproached, (as the peaceable peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God have been in almoſt every age, and evil-minded men may ſurmiſe evil againſt them; yet ſuch a one who rules for God, (and not to pleaſe mens humours) will not afflict and trouble inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and peaceable people, upon the ſuppoſitions of envious and evil-minded men, becauſe he ſees there is no (nor can be any) evil-doing proved againſt them, that they are guilty of.</p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:56124:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <p> And Friend, if ſuch a heart and mind were found in thee, thou wouldſt be happy and honourable indeed; I ſay, if it were in thy heart thus to act even in that very way and manner before-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to look after, and puniſh evil-doers, and to ſtop and limit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs and wickedneſs, to encourage and be a praiſe to thoſe that do well, that are peaceable and harmleſs among men, that ſerve and worſhip the Lord in his own way, (and not after the inventions and preſcriptions of men) even in that way which his own ſpirit leads and perſwades them unto, then it would go well with thee, and thou mighteſt then know the worth and exceeding preciouſneſs of having the peace of Conſcience, if thou didſt act in this way which is according to that of God therein, which would lead thee and all men to this, did they but give ear unto it, and follow its counſel; and then would wickedneſs be ſtopped, and godlineſs, ſobriety and honeſty, would be eſteemed and promoted: But alas! how doth the contrary abound in this place? and how has wickedneſs its ſwing? and how are evil-doers encreaſing, drunkenneſs, ſwearing, and vain ſports and playes, allowed and tollerated? And theſe are not accounted unlawful Meetings: But for peaceable people, young children and youth, that have inclination after godlineſs and ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to meet together for no other end but to worſhip God, this is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted an unlawful Aſſembly, (for there was never, nor can never any thing elſe be proved againſt us, what ever ſuch as have enmity in their hearts againſt us, may imagine) and muſt now be broken. And in this work thou haſt appeared, in cauſing thy Neighbours to be haled out of their Chriſtian Aſſemblies, and ſent to Gaol from their honeſt Callings and Employments, ſeparating men from their Wives and Children, and Wives from their Husbands, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from their Parents, whereby they may be deſtroyed; and all this, only becauſe of the exerciſe of their Conſciences towards God, and for their obedience to him. And oh how heavy a burden will this be upon thee one day, that thou ſhouldſt have a hand in this, and joyn with that ſpirit of Perſecution againſt thy peaceable Neighbours, and young children, whom thou canſt not but be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in thy conſcience, that they are peaceable, and intends no ſuch thing as to plot againſt the King; neither is it a likely thing to any judicious man, that a few Lads and young Girls, and a few wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſhould meet together to plot or contrive inſurrections, and no
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56124:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuch thing can be, or ever will be proved againſt the people in ſcorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are led by that ſpirit of truth which leads into love and peace, and good-will towards all men, though evil reports and falſe accuſations may be given out againſt us, and many fooliſh ſtories may go about among ſuch as are given up to believe lyes, which are incredible to a man of gravity and underſtanding; yet our innocency, uprightneſs and honeſty, will appear, when all theſe things will dye, and the refuge of lyes is ſwept away; and that truth, and way of life, peace, and eternal happineſs, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch God hath made known unto us, will more and more be made manifeſt to be that way in which alone true love, peace, unity and concord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men is enjoyed; and without the knowledg of which; men can never be eſtabliſhed in peace and unity, where no plotters nor contrivers of miſchief againſt any man, can come; and which all that are out of, are not to be truſted, whatever they may in words and ſhews pretend; for ſuch as do tranſgreſs againſt the Light of Gods Spirit in their own Conſciences, and are unfaithful and treacherous to that, will alſo in time be ſo unto men, though they may fawn and flatter for their own ends, all which we do utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny, and in our ſouls abhor, and which the Truth which we have received, hath led and redeemed us out of.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore Friend, it was upon my heart to caution thee to take heed what thou doſt, as to proceed in this work of perſecution of innocent people for the exerciſe of their conſciences in the ſervice and worſhip of God, and cauſing thy peaceable Neighbours to be haled to priſons for their obedience to the Lord God; for this will kindle the wrath of the Lord againſt thee, and be the cauſe of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s heavy judgments to come and fall upon thee in the end, and ſorrow and trouble will take hold of thee, when the Witneſs of God in thy own conſcience ſhall bring theſe unchriſtian-like proceedings againſt thoſe that did thee, nor no man wrong, into thy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and give the ſentence of condemnation upon thee for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning, and joyning with the perſecuting ſpirit, againſt the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and ſuch as fears and reverences his Name.</p>
                     <p>And though now ſome may over-awe thee, telling thee there is a Law, and thou may think to cover thy ſelf, by ſaying the Law is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us; yet I ſay, that will not excuſe thee in the dreadful day of account; for there was a Law which the Jews had againſt our
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56124:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> Lord Jeſus Chriſt, yet that would not excuſe thoſe that condemned him: But yet this Law doth not at all reach us, being rightly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, becauſe we meet really in truth to worſhip the Lord, and to perform holy duty to him, and not in any colour or pretence, to plot or contrive inſurrections; for they that do ſo, are the perſons that the Law takes hold of; and though ſome may ſuſpect otherwiſe of us, yet that is not ſufficient ground ſo violently to proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy peaceable Neighbours upon a bare ſuppoſition, becauſe it hath not, nor can ever be proved, that we have done, or intend any ſuch thing at our Meetings; and therefore we are grievouſly wronged and abuſed, and the Law turned to a wrong end, even againſt them that are peaceable, and againſt whom it was not made, according to the Preamble of it.</p>
                     <p>And therefore it will be well for thee to be cool and conſiderate in thy mind, and not raſhly to run (or be led) on without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Lord, or fear to offend and grieve his good ſpirit in thy ſelf, which will not always ſtrive; or without any pity or compaſſion (as a man) to thy Neighbours, to ſend them to priſon, from their Wives, Children, Husbands and Parents, and Families, as if they were ſuch intollerable offenders, that were not worthy of the common air in the Creation; when all that can be proved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, is, That they were in ſuch a houſe, and they ſaid to wait upon, or worſhip God: And is this now become ſuch a crime? Oh that ever men that profeſs Chriſtianity, ſhould be ſo blind and ſottiſh, as to loſe their very reaſon (as men) to act in this manner, which generations to come will even abhor. And who would have thought that the Magiſtrates and people of <hi>Reading</hi> ſhould be found in this work beyond moſt in the Nation? What, is there not drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards and ſwearers to be looked after? And do not theſe tranſgreſs the Law? Is there not a Law againſt drunkards and ſwearers? and art thou ſo forward and diligent to execute that, as thou (with others) art that which you ſay is againſt our Meetings? Are not ſuch at liberty? And are not theſe things which are ſins againſt the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, winked at, and lightly paſſed over? And muſt thoſe whom you do only ſuſpect (or ſome of you) to be tranſgreſſors of mans Law be ſo violently proceeded againſt, when nothing of fact can be proved againſt them, nor no man can juſtly charge them of doing any evil againſt him?</p>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:56124:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <p> Conſider of theſe things, and lay them to heart, and beware what thou doſt, leſt thou be found ſtriving againſt that which God hath purpoſed to exalt; and remember what one once ſaid, <hi>If this way be of God, it will ſtand,</hi> let men do what they can; and if it be not, it will fall of its ſelf, they need not trouble themſelves about it. And if you that profeſs your ſelves Chriſtians, had ſo much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and moderation as he that was a Heathen, you would not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your ſelves ſo much as you do, which will be in vain to ſtrive againſt the Lord, who will exalt his own Name and Truth over your heads, though you may be permitted to try many, in which the Lord is trying of you in this your day, which it would be well if you could ſee, which you can never do till you return your minds to that Principle of God in you, which will let you ſee your ſelves, and how you ſtand, and convinceth of ſin, and leads out of it all ſuch as do ſincerely love and follow it; and all ſuch as do ſlight and diſregard it, it will be a worm gnawing in their Conſciences, and a fire that will never be quenched; which will make the proud to bow, and conſume and lay low the glory and haughtineſs of all fleſh, and bring eternal ſorrow and anguiſh upon all that have lived wantonly upon earth, and ſpent their time in pleaſure and vanity, in eaſe and fulneſs: The day of the Lord is at hand, which will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the wicked as a thief in the night; and bleſſed will they be that haſt and prepare to meet him, by putting off their ſins, and turning from their iniquities, and forſaking the evil way; which that thou mayeſt do, is my deſire; however I have cleared my conſcience unto thee, and reſt a true lover of thy ſoul.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Reading-Gaol</hi> 
                           <date>the 3<hi>d</hi> day of the 3<hi>d</hi> month, 1665.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>From a Sufferer for the teſtimony of a good Conſcience, and for keeping the command of the Lord Jeſus, in which I have peace with him, which no man can take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. J. C.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:56124:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> The Aſſizes being holden at <hi>Abingdon</hi> the <hi>7th</hi> and <hi>8th</hi> days of the <hi>5th</hi> Month called <hi>July,</hi> 1665; to which place Twenty ſix of the Priſoners were brought by the Gaoler, <hi>viz.</hi> The twenty one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, who at the Seſſions at <hi>Newberry</hi> were put off to the Aſſizes to have their Tryal, and <hi>A Curtis,</hi> and <hi>S. Lamboll,</hi> who were committed as dangerous and ſuſpicious perſons; and the other three were, <hi>Chriſtopher Cheeſeman, A. Sharp,</hi> and <hi>S. Binfield,</hi> who were committed on the third account for meeting, and were called to the Barr before Judg <hi>Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rell,</hi> who (after ſome queſtions of Name place of abode, what they were, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> ſaid to the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers at the Barr:</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What, you go to unlawful Meetings and Conventicles, and will not obey the Kings Laws,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>One of the Priſoners anſwered, I am clear from all evil againſt the King, and of all Plots and contriving Inſurrections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for our doors ſtand open, and our Meetings are publick, (not in holes nor corners) where any that will, may come.</p>
               <p>So they were put by.</p>
               <p>And having much ado to patch up an Indictment againſt <hi>Chriſto: Cheeſeman,</hi> there being no record of his ſecond offence according to the Act; for he was never taken and committed on the ſecond account; being in a ſtrait, they called for <hi>Chriſtoph: Cheeſemans</hi> Commitment; which being given to the Judg, he asked if thoſe were all the Commitments?</p>
               <p>The Gaoler anſwered, <hi>Yes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Judg finding no ſecond Commitment, turned to <hi>W. Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Your beſt way is to let him go, and take him again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon which Juſtice <hi>Alſeworth</hi> ſtood up and ſaid to the Judg, <hi>If you let this man go, he will go about the Count<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y preaching, and do much hurt, before you can take him again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then they proceeded, and called the three perſons before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and read an Indictment agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt two of them, viz. <hi>C. Cheeſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Sharp;</hi> to which they pleaded, Not guilty.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen the Judg called to <hi>S. Binfield,</hi> and asked what age ſhe was? But ſhe not anſwering, the Judg called out in the Court, ſaying, <hi>Who knows what age ſhe is of?</hi> No anſwer being made, he ſaid to her, <hi>I think you are but fifteen years old; and by that time you are ſixteen, I</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:56124:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>hore you will have more wit.</hi> So ſhe was freed as under age, it being but the ſecond time of her commitment, it was ſuppoſed they would not meddl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any farther with her upon that account.</p>
               <p>So the Indictment being read againſt the other two, which was very falſe in many particulars; as, <hi>That</hi> Chriſtopher Cheeſeman, <hi>with other evil perſons, to the number of five, did meet in contempt of the Kings Laws, and to the diſturbance of the people,</hi> &amp;c. and much more of the ſame na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure.</p>
               <p>A Jury being called, ſome of whom were ſo drunk, that they were hardly able to ſpeak or ſtand, but as they were ſupported by others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the throng.</p>
               <p>Priſoner ſaid, I deſire there may be ſome Witneſs produced to prove that I go to any ſuch Meetings to plot againſt the King, and that I have at any time been taken at ſuch a Meeting; for we meet in the fear of the Lord, and our Meetings tend to holineſs of life, and love and unity among our Neighbours; and this the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth exhort men unto; and here is the Law (having it in his hand) which ſpeaks poſitively to the matter, as in the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Clauſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reamble to the Act, which ſhews the very grounds and reaſons wherefore the Act was made, viz. To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent plotting and contriving Inſurrections, as appears farther by the words of the Act, which ſaith, <hi>That if any perſon of the age of ſixteen years, ſhall be preſent at any Aſſembly, Conventicle or Meeting; under colour or pretence of any exerciſe of Religion, in other manner then is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Liturgy,</hi> &amp;c. (which doth allow, that in all places, and at all times men ought to perform holy duties to God, and to ſeek him, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> Now if any Witneſs can come and ſwear, That I was there upon ſuch account, then let me ſuffer the penalty which the Act provides. Therefore I deſire the Witneſs may be produced to prove what is falſly ſuggeſted againſt me.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is no part of the Law, the whole body of the Law fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth;</hi> calling to the Clerk to read the Law; ſo he read that clauſe, <hi>If any perſons to the number of five, or upward, under pretence of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences, ſhall meet in exerciſe of Religious Worſhip, contrary to what the Liturgy doth allow,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>after lawful conviction of the third offence, ſentence of tranſportation ſhall be given,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. Cheeſeman.</speaker>
                  <p>The Law doth not ſay, that people ſhould not meet really to worſhip God; nor yet injoyn them where, or what houſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56124:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> to meet in; but ſaith; That if any perſons to the number of five, or upward, ſhall under pretence of Religious Worſhip, meet to Plot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That's no pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t of the Law.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priſ</speaker>
                  <p>The Law was made to prevent plotting and contriving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections; that was the ground and cauſe wherefore the Act was made, (and not, I hope, to hinder any people from worſhipping of God, or to make them offenders for ſeeking him) ſo unleſs it can be proved, that I was found plotting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this Act concerns me not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here are the Regiſters under the hands of the Juſtices; and here is Sir</hi> William Armorer, <hi>an honourable Gentleman, that is one of them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                  <p>He is honourable, that is a vertuous man.</p>
                  <p>But the Reader may take notice, that there was no Record for the ſecond offence; for the Priſoner was never committed on a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You are an impudent fellow.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not an impudent fellow, but do ſpeak the truth; for <hi>William Armorer</hi> is a common Enemy to me, and hath uſed violence towards me divers times; and he is a partial man, and therefore no competent Witneſs; and I have much to ſay againſt him, and do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that Witneſs may be brought forth, if there be any, to prove the breach of the Law; for there are two principal clauſes in the Act, upon which you ought to inſiſt for tryal of me. The firſt is, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it can be proved, that I under pretence of tender Conſcience, did meet to plot againſt the King, and contrive Inſurrections among the People. And ſecondly, Whether I did meet, and was found ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing in Religious Worſhip, contrary to what the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth allow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I tell you, That the Clauſe in the Preamble of the Act, is no part of the Law.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis the very ground and ſubſtance of the Act and Law made againſt unlawful Meetings; Such that under pretence of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſcience, do meet to plot againſt the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ours is no ſuch Meeting, neither hath there been any witneſs from firſt to laſt, to prove any ſuch thing againſt me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We have witneſs here, if need be,</hi> (looking about him in the Court) but none appeared.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:56124:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Take heed what thou doſt, for it is the Cauſe of God, and matter of Conſcience towards God only, for which I am this day called in queſtion.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Judg ſaid, <hi>'Tis no matter for Conſcience, but for diſobeying the Kings Laws.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I do affirm as in the preſence of the Lord, That 'tis matter of Conſcience only, and nothing elſe; and there is no proof of any thing to the contrary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well, Jury, you hear how 'tis, and what the Law ſaith, That upon proof made before the Juſtices againſt ſuch offenders, ſhall be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Conviction; and here are the Regiſters</hi> (though there was no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond offence) <hi>under the hands of the ſaid Juſtices.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                  <p>You that are of the Jury, I know not the faces of any one of you, therefore I leave it to you without any exceptions, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that you would take notice, That 'tis matter of conſcience on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for the Law ſaith, <hi>That if any under pretence of tender Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſhall meet to plot againſt the King, and to contrive Inſurrections, or to exerciſe in Religious Worſhip contrary to what the Liturgy of the Church of England doth allow, &amp;c.</hi> So that there ought to be proof made that I was found (under the aforeſaid pretence) plotting <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and exerciſing in Religious Worſhip contrary to what the Liturgy doth allow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You of the Jury, you have heard what he ſaith; they would be interpreters of the Laws, and ſpiritual things too: you hear what the Law ſaith, That if any perſons to the number of five, or upward, ſhall meet together in exerciſe of Religious Worſhip, contrary to what the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy alloweth, upon proof thereof made before the Juſtices and Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters under their hands,</hi> (but here was neither Witneſſes, nor but one Regiſter of the firſt offence; for there was no ſecond, as is ſaid, and therefore the Judg would have had <hi>W. Armo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er</hi> have let him go) <hi>ſhall be ſufficient Conviction. Jury, go together.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>But the Jury went not from the Barr, neither did they call to ſee the Regiſter under the hands of the fore-mentioned Juſtices, nor yet for any other witneſs or teſtimony, whereby to be ſatisfied con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Priſoner, but rather like drunken men, not valuing the Liberty or life of a free-born Engliſh man.</p>
               <p>In a ſmall time, the Judg having them near him, ſaid, <hi>Jury, what ſay you, Guilty or not guilty?</hi> And two or three of them anſwered, <hi>Guilty.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:56124:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <speaker>Judg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What have you to ſay for your ſelf, that ſentence of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſportation may not be paſt againſt you?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I have much to ſay for my ſelf, and for the Cauſe for which I am this day called in queſtion; for 'tis the Cauſe of God, praiſed be the Lord who has judged me worthy to bear teſtimony to his Name this day—</p>
               </sp>
               <p>The Judg called to the Clerk to read ſentence.</p>
               <p>So the Clerk took the Act, and read that Clauſe which ſaith, That ſuch offender being lawfully convict, ſhall be tranſported beyond the Seas for ſeven years; and if he return before that time be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, to be proceeded againſt as a Felon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other Priſoner, <hi>Anne Sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p,</hi> pleading alſo, That there was never no witneſs from firſt to laſt, appeared to their faces to prove a third offence. Howbeit, ſhe was alſo ſentenced to lye in priſon twelve Months, being a woman under covert. So were both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Gaol.</p>
               <p>The other twenty one priſoners, who were by the Juſtices at their Seſſions, ordered to the Aſſizes, were brought to the place afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, in order to their Tryal, were not called, but returned back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the Seſſiions, which was holden the <hi>11th</hi> day of the ſame month, at the ſame place; and the proceedings was much on this wiſe <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anne Curtis,</hi> and <hi>Sarah Lamboll</hi> being called, nothing was laid to their charge of danger and ſuſpition, as was mentioned in the order of Seſſions; but they tendered the Oath of Allegiance again to them, and returned them back again to the Gaol.</p>
               <p>The next day, being the <hi>12th</hi> of the month, the twenty one pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners upon the account of the Oath, were called to the Barr, and an Indictment was read againſt them, <hi>(Tho: Holt</hi> of <hi>Abingdon</hi> being Judg) to this purpoſe, That they had wilfully and obſtinately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the Oath of Allegiance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which the Priſoners pleaded Not guilty, and demanded a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of the Indictment, but never had it. So the Gaoler had them back again to the Gaol.</p>
               <p>Again the 23<hi>d</hi> of the ſame Month, <hi>W. Armorer</hi> came to the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and <hi>Tho: Kenton</hi> Mayor, and took <hi>Eliz: Tudway, Mary Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and <hi>Judeth Smith,</hi> and ſent them to the Gaol on the third ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, though it was but <hi>Eliz: Tudways</hi> ſecond. Alſo ſent <hi>Joan Dee</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:56124:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> to the Gaol for ſix months. And <hi>Hannah Emerton, Ellin Binfeild, John Walker,</hi> and <hi>Henry Day,</hi> to the Houſe of Correction for three months.</p>
               <p>The <hi>27th</hi> of the <hi>6th</hi> month, called <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1665, <hi>W. Armorer</hi> and <hi>Edward Dolby</hi> came to the Meeting, and took <hi>Eliz: Kemboll, Hannah Kent,</hi> and <hi>Mary Lamboll,</hi> and ſent them to the Gaol on the firſt account; and <hi>Thomas Conicke, Joſeph Phipps,</hi> and <hi>John Thorn,</hi> to the Houſe of Correction; <hi>Thomas Conicke</hi> for ſix months, the other two for three months.</p>
               <p>The third of the eighth month called <hi>October,</hi> the Seſſions was held at <hi>Newberry,</hi> to which the above-named <hi>Eliz: Tudway, Mary Winter,</hi> and <hi>Judeth Smith,</hi> were brought; the Bill being found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, they were indicted on the third Offence, ſo called and having pleaded Not guilty, were ſent back again to Gaol, and to be tryed the next Seſſions following.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>9th</hi> of the <hi>11th</hi> Month called <hi>January,</hi> 1665, the Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was holden at <hi>Reading,</hi> where <hi>Anthony Barker</hi> of <hi>Sunning,</hi> ſate as Judg.</p>
               <p>The ſame evening before the Court broke up, the Clerk <hi>(Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion)</hi> called to the Gaoler to bring the Quakers in the morning; and <hi>W. Armo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> bid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem get a good Jury.</p>
               <p>Accord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gly the next morning early they were had to the Town-Hall, and called to the Barr, all the twenty one Priſoners, except <hi>John Paine,</hi> (who could not go, being ſick in his bed) and a Jury was pickt according to <hi>W. Armore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> deſire, one <hi>Charles Belwood</hi> being one, who was formerly <hi>W. Armorers</hi> Coach-man, <hi>John Auſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> the Shoomaker, and <hi>Daniel Seamer</hi> the Taylor, <hi>Will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>age</hi> the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and one <hi>Cooper,</hi> commonly called a Conjurer, and ſome others like them, and one who is a Papiſt, (as the people did inform us) but the Priſoners objected againſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me of them; for on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel Seamer,</hi> had ſaid in open Court, at a Seſſions held at <hi>Newbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> That he hated them as he hated the Devil: But Juſtice <hi>Pamer</hi> of <hi>Oakingham,</hi> ſaid, Unleſs you will take your Oaths of that, we will not put any of them out of the Jury, though he knew they made conſcience of an Oath.</p>
               <p>So he, among the reſt, ſtood in the Jury, which were their Judges, and the Indictment being read, That they wilfully and obſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nately refuſed to take the Oath of Allegiance, mentioned in the third of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56124:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> King <hi>James, &amp;c.</hi> The Priſoners pleaded, firſt, That there was no Statute did impower them to tender them this Oath. Secondly, That it was not the Oath mentioned in the third of King <hi>James,</hi> becauſe they tendered it to them by the Name of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second. Thirdly, That it was not according to Law; for the Law ſaith it ſhould firſt be tendered to them ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Seſſions; and the ground of ſuch tender ſhould be upon ſome preſentment or complaint from ſome Ordinary, or others, and then a tender in Seſſions, and that by the major part of the Juſtices.</p>
               <p>All which things, and much more, as in that caſe is proved in the Statute, ought to have been firſt, which hath not been to us.</p>
               <p>Then ſtood up <hi>Edward Dolby</hi> a Councellor, ſaying, That if two Juſtices had power to tender it out of Seſſions, they had, no doubt, as much power to tender it in Seſſions upon complaint, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One of the Priſoners bid them take notice it muſt be upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt: But it was not ſo tendered to them, but as a ſnare, after they were cleared by the Jury, knowing that they could not ſwear in any caſe.</p>
               <p>Much more the Priſoners had to ſay, but they would not hear them, but called to <hi>Champion</hi> the Clerk, and one <hi>Staples</hi> a Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, to ſwear that the Oath had been tendered to them according to Law.</p>
               <p>Being done, the Jury went forth. Being returned again, the Judg asked if they were agreed on their Verdict?</p>
               <p>Who anſwered, <hi>Yes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He asked, Whether guilty, or not guilty?</p>
               <p>To which the Fore-man anſwered, That ſo many as the Oath was legally tendered unto, and they refuſed to take it, ſo many were guilty.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>William Armorer</hi> and the Clerk ſaid, It was legally tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them all.</p>
               <p>One of the Jury, <hi>Charles Belwood,</hi> replyes, <hi>Yes, yes,</hi> then they are all guilty.</p>
               <p>But many of the ſtanders by ſaid it was a ſpecial Verdict, the Priſoners not being ſuffered to come to the Barr to hear it, and one of the Priſoners being ſick in his bed at the Gaol, as before is ſaid.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:56124:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> So the Court being adjourned till after dinner, and being come together again, they called the Priſoners to the Barr to hear their ſentence; but ſome of the Priſoners told them, they did not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that the Jury had brought them in guilty; but they would not hear them. And one of the Priſoners told them he had an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Judgment. But the Judge, <hi>Anthony Barker,</hi> ſaid, They had time enough for that, and then ſaid, <hi>Hear your ſentence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe you have refuſed the Oath of Allegiance, and the Jury hath found you guilty, you have incurr'd the Penalty of a Premunire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after ſome words ſpoken by the Priſoners to them, they were had away to the Gaol; for they were reſolved to do their work, if not with the Law, without the Law, and their reward accordingly they ſhall receive; and the Judg, <hi>A. Barker,</hi> is ſince dead.</p>
               <p>But the ſame day, by the ſame Jury, <hi>Eliz: Tudway, Judeth Smith,</hi> and <hi>Mary Winter,</hi> were tryed upon the third account formeeting; and though it could never be proved that <hi>Eliz: Tudway</hi> had be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n twice convict, yet had <hi>W. Armorer</hi> and <hi>Tho: Seikes,</hi> ſet their hands and ſeals that they were all upon the third account.</p>
               <p>Upon which <hi>Eliz: Tudway</hi> (knowing the thing to be falſe) ſent preſently a Meſſenger to <hi>Tho: Seikes,</hi> to know whether ever he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted her to priſon while he was Mayor. His anſwer was, he could not tell; but if his hand were to it, it muſt needs be ſo.</p>
               <p>The Priſoner ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaking ſomething concerning their unjuſt proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings again her; the Clerk, <hi>Champion,</hi> ſaid, ſhe deſerved to have her mouth ſtopt with a handkerchief.</p>
               <p>So the Jury brought them in guilty; and the Judg, <hi>A. Barker,</hi> paſt ſentence againſt <hi>Mary Winter,</hi> and <hi>Judeth Smith,</hi> to be ſent to <hi>Barbadoes, &amp;c.</hi> and that <hi>Eliz. Tudway</hi> ſhould lye in priſon twelve Months, being under covert; the Judg being in ſome confuſion, would have ſentenced her for time of life, had it not been prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome that ſtood by.</p>
               <p>The next that were called, was <hi>A. Curtis, S. Lamboll,</hi> and <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> who was fetcht out of his own houſe in <hi>Newberry,</hi> at a Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions time, and had to the Court for opening his ſhop-windows on one of their Faſt-dayes, whom they alſo enſnared with the Oath of Allegiance. And being indicted for wilfully and obſtinately refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Oath of Allegiance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they pleaded Not guilty; and the Clerk asked them whether they would enter their Recognizance?</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:56124:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> One of the Priſoners asked, What they did mean by it?</p>
               <p>The Clerk anſwered, The Court is willing to favour you, and to let you have liberty till next Seſſions, giving Sureties.</p>
               <p>The Priſoners anſwered, They had no Sureties; but if they would take their words, they would promiſe to appear if they were well.</p>
               <p>Which not being taken, they were returned to the Gaol.</p>
               <p>The next day a ſufficient man of the Town (hearing that the Court had proffered to let them have their liberty upon Security, till the next Seſſions) went to the Clerk of the Seſſions, and prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to be their Security till the next Seſſions; that is to ſay, for A. <hi>Curtis,</hi> and <hi>S. Lamboll.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Clerk told him he could not do it without an Order under the hands of two Juſtices of Peace.</p>
               <p>So he went to <hi>W. Armorer,</hi> but he would not take Sureties for them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>14th</hi> day of the ſame Month, <hi>W. Armorer</hi> his man came to the Meeting, and ſeeing Friends meet together, went out and pull'd the door after him, (the Meeting being in a room next the ſtreet) it being a ſpring-lock, catcht; ſo he lockt himſelf out.</p>
               <p>In a little after, his Maſter came in great rage, and called to Friends to open the door, or elſe he would break all the Glaſs Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows. But the Friends in the Meeting ſate ſtill; for as they had no hand in ſhutting of him out, they were not willing to let him in Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he called for a Smith and a Sledg, there being <hi>Ranold Thornberry</hi> the Conſtable, and one <hi>Richard Davis,</hi> that uſes to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on the Butchers, and ſome others with him; the Sledg being brought, with many blows they forc't open the door, and <hi>W. Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> looking in, ſaid, He is not here: Whereby it appeared, that he had information of ſome perſon that was not there. So having ſet ſome to keep the Friends in the Meeting, he went to an inner door of the Houſe of <hi>Tho: Curtis,</hi> and broke that open, and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Court, the Wood-houſe, Brew-houſe, Stable, and Hey-loft, and then broke the door into the houſe, and after that, broke ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther door to go up ſtairs; and finding one Chamber-door lockt, though the Key was in it, yet he broke the lock and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he door to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and entred into the room, and ſearched all the houſe from the bottom to the top, no body being in the houſe, the Maid-ſervant
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:56124:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> being gone to priſon to carry Neceſſaries to her Maſter and Miſtriſs. What was loſt, is unknown, excepting a knife and a bolt. A ſtander-by affirms, That <hi>Whitcher</hi> the Taylor, <hi>Daniel Seamer</hi> his Son-in-law, told him, That they went into the houſe to ſearch for writings, and to ſee how the houſe was furniſhed. Having broke open ſix doors, and ſearched the houſe, came forth again to the Meeting-room, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Friends to be had to the Counter; and after their Worſhip was ended (it being the firſt day of the week, which they call their Sabbath, on which day he uſually doth this work) he ſent for them to his houſe before himſelf, and <hi>Edw: Dolby;</hi> and becauſe three of the Friends, being young men, did not put off their hats to him, he <hi>(W. Armorer)</hi> called to his man to fill them with water; the man not doing it preſently, he gave him a kick on the breech: Then his man took the Hats, and filled them with water. <hi>W. Armorer</hi> bid him ſet them down full on the ground; being done, ſaid, <hi>Now let them put them on their heads.</hi> But the Conſtable threw the water out, and gave them their hats again, it being very cold weather.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>W. Armorer</hi> called the young Maidens, whom he took alſo at the Meeting, and ſtripped up their ſleeves, and asked them if they had any black ſtrings or ribbons: And having done, let them go. So cauſed a Mittimus to be made for the three young men, viz. <hi>Joſeph Phipps, Henry Adams,</hi> and <hi>John Thorn,</hi> and ſent them to the Houſe of Correction for ſix months, and ſent <hi>Anne Webb</hi> to the ſame place for three months, and <hi>Anne Sharp</hi> to the Gaol for three months; and in ſome dayes after, he ſent privately for that Mittimus, and charges that ſhe ſhould not ſee or know of it; and ſent another Mittimus for <hi>Anne Sharp</hi> to be kept a Priſoner for twelve Months.</p>
               <p>The <hi>15th</hi> of the ſecond Month called <hi>April,</hi> 1666, came <hi>W. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morer</hi> and <hi>Edw: Dolby</hi> to the Meeting, with <hi>Ranold Thornberry,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, where was <hi>Robert Paine, Anne Hatt, Hannah Emerton, Eliz: Tudway, Mary Webb, Mary Kent,</hi> and <hi>Sarah Kent;</hi> and after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny words, W. A. bid the Conſtable take them to the Counter.</p>
               <p>One of the Friends ſaid, there was not the number, Five of age.</p>
               <p>He ſaid, he would take them if there were but one of age, if there were four children; and ſaid it was the Chanchellors Judgment.</p>
               <p>And being had to the Counter (the Town-Priſon) after their Worſhip was done, he committed <hi>Hannah Emerton</hi> to the Houſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:56124:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> of Correction for ſix Months, <hi>Robert Paine</hi> for three months, and <hi>Anne Hatt</hi> for ſix months, to the Gaol; and <hi>Eliz: Tudway</hi> for twelve months; and then ſaid, he would make all them that were under the age of ſixteen years, pay twelve pence a piece.</p>
               <p>The <hi>24th</hi> of the ſecond Month, called <hi>April,</hi> 1666, <hi>Anne Curtis</hi> and <hi>Sarah Lamboll</hi> were had to the Seſſions at <hi>Newberry,</hi> in order to their tryal; but <hi>W. Armorer</hi> not being there, they were not called. <hi>Anne Curtis</hi> ſpeaking with divers of the Juſtices at a private houſe, relating the manner of the proceedings againſt them, demanded of them a Trial, being brought for that end; and if the Jury did find them guilty, they were willing to ſuffer; if not, they ſhould clear them.</p>
               <p>And after ſome words, they bid her withdraw.</p>
               <p>And meeting with Juſtice <hi>Doleman</hi> in the ſtreet, who knew her, ſhe related their caſe as to the other. He anſwered; He would go to the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>Loveleſs,</hi> and the Juſtices, and tell them her buſineſs, and bring her word what might be done.</p>
               <p>And after ſome time, he came again to her Lodging, and told-her, That the King's Evidence was not ready, and therefore they could not have their Trial: and that the Juſtices thought it an unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing that they ſhould be put from Seſſions to Seſſions, and ſtill kept in priſon; therefore you may have your liberty, giving your words to appear the next Seſſions.</p>
               <p>To which ſhe anſwered, We proffered our words to appear, the laſt Seſſions, and it would not be taken.</p>
               <p>He replyed, But it will now; and that they did intend to write a Letter to Sir <hi>W. Armorer,</hi> to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>So ſhe ſaid, If they would have us to appear, we ſhall, if well, and at liberty.</p>
               <p>So they returned to <hi>Reading,</hi> to their own Houſes.</p>
               <p>But the next day <hi>W. Armorer</hi> ſent the Gaolers man to fetch them in to priſon again. The man told W. A. That the Juſtices had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them liberty till the next Seſſions. At which he was very angry, and replyed, What have the Juſtices to do with MY PRISONERS? and threatned that he would lay him by the heels, if he did not fetch them in.</p>
               <p>So he fetcht in <hi>S. Lamboll;</hi> but A. <hi>Curtis</hi> was gone with her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toward <hi>Briſtol,</hi> to ſee her Relations; and at her return, hearing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56124:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> that he was angry with the Under-keeper, ſhe went to him, telling him of it, viz. That ſhe heard he was angry with the Under-Gaoler becauſe he had not fetcht her in; and that ſhe would not have any one have anger for what ſhe did; and thought ſhe went in her own right, as having liberty from the Juſtices till the next Seſſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. Armorer</hi> anſwered, 'Twas no ſuch thing.</p>
               <p>To which ſhe replyed, ſhe knew nothing but what he they call Sir <hi>Thomas Doleman,</hi> told her, repeating to him what he had ſaid to her at <hi>Newberry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then W. A. ſaid, If ſhe would give ſecurity, ſhe ſhould have her liberty; if not, he would ſend her to her Husband.</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Curtis</hi> replyed, I perceive it was the reſt of the Juſtices de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, we ſhould have our liberty, but thee only oppoſeſt it.</p>
               <p>And he anſwered, Yes, it is I; and ſaid the Juſtices did it in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to him, (and yet this man all along pretended great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to her for her Fathers ſake.)</p>
               <p>Much more was ſpoken, too much here to mention.</p>
               <p>And a few dayes after, he ſent <hi>Ranold Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> Conſtable, with a Warrant, to apprehend her, but not being at home, miſt her at that time.</p>
               <p>The <hi>19th</hi> of the <hi>4th</hi> month, called <hi>June,</hi> 1666, <hi>John Withram</hi> the Under-Sherif of the County, with one <hi>Thomas Roſſe</hi> the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utor, came to the Gaol, and called for <hi>Tho: Curtis</hi> and <hi>Geo: Lamboll,</hi> and told them they had a Warrant from the King to ſeize upon their Eſtates; and preſently <hi>Geo: Thorp</hi> and they two went into their Chambers, and ſeized on all their Books, Papers and Writings, and on 1501. in money of <hi>Tho: Curtis</hi>'s, (there was more money loſt in his room, it was judged about fourteen pound, but they ſaid they had it not) and when they came down again, they locked them out of their rooms, and went to the Houſe of <hi>Thomas Curtis,</hi> and looked over his Good, and ſeized on it; and then went to tbe Houſe of <hi>Geo: Lamboll,</hi> and did the like there, and took an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventory of all they could find; but did not remove the Goods, for they promiſed to be accountable for them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame day W, A. ſent <hi>Edward Lawrence,</hi> Conſtable, with a Warrant to apprehend <hi>A. Curtis,</hi> and had her preſently away to the Gaol.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:56124:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> And ſome time after, he ſent to the Gaol for <hi>A. C.</hi> and being come to him, he told her, That the Gentlemen who were concerned in her Husbands Eſtate, deſired me to ſet you at liberty; and here is your diſcharge, giving it into her hand. A true Copy whereof, here in after followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="discharge">
                           <opener>
                              <dateline>Burgus de Reading in Com. Berks.</dateline>
                           </opener>
                           <head>To the Keeper of His Majeſty's Gaol for the ſaid Burrough, and to his Deputy and Deputies there, Greeting.</head>
                           <p>THeſe are in the Name of the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, to charge and command you immediately upon ſight hereof to ſet at liberty and free the body of <hi>Anne Curtis,</hi> Wife of <hi>Thomas Curtis,</hi> of this Burrough, Woolen-Draper, out of your cuſtody, and from her Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <date>Dated under my hand and ſeal the 22d day of Auguſt, Anno Dom. 1666.</date>
                              <signed>W. Armorer.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>The <hi>29th</hi> day of the fifth Month called <hi>July,</hi> (66) came <hi>VV. Armorer</hi> and <hi>Edward Dolby</hi> to the Meeting again, and looking into the Meeting, left his man at the door, and went into the Houſe, and ſearched from Room to Room and under the Beds, pretending that ſome were gone out of the Meeting, and found onely four of age, ſent two of them to the Gaol, and the two other, <hi>viz. Joſeph Phipps</hi> and <hi>Hanah Kent,</hi> he ſent to the Houſe of Correction, <hi>I. P.</hi> for three Months, and <hi>Hanah Kent</hi> for ſix Months, and demanded of <hi>Lydia He ſant, Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y Kent</hi> and <hi>Sarah Kent,</hi> Twelve pence a piece, for not being at his Church that day, they being under age, for not paying of which, he ſent them to the Gaol, where they have been priſoners above twelve Months; and another Child, <hi>Eliz: Whithart</hi> being taken with them at the ſame Meeting, having but one Arm,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:56124:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> a Neighbour having told him that her Father was dead, and that it was judged the cauſe of his death, was his being kept long in Priſon, through <hi>(W. Armorer)</hi> his means, in the extream cold weather, at laſt he let her go.</p>
               <p>The <hi>19th</hi> of the <hi>6th</hi> Month called <hi>Auguſt</hi> (66) <hi>Anne Hatt</hi> (who was committed for ſix Months, onely for being at a Meeting, to wait upon, and Worſhip the Lord in Spirit and in Truth, being kept in, in the heat of Summer in the Gaol, where <hi>W. Armorer</hi> had thronged up ſo many together, and cauſed to be kept in ſo cloſe, that he could not endure to hear of one abroad) dyed in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and finiſhed her Teſtimony for the Lord and his Truth, being found faithful in her day, in which ſhe walked in Gravity, Sobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the fear of the Lord, whoſe end is bleſſed among the holy Martyrs for evermore.</p>
               <p>The <hi>15th</hi> of the <hi>11th</hi> Month called <hi>January,</hi> 1666, The Seſſions began at <hi>Reading,</hi> and the next day being the <hi>16th</hi> day, <hi>Joſeph Phipps</hi> and <hi>Sarah Lamboll</hi> were called to the Barr; But the Jury being gone out upon the Tryal of a Friend that was committed on another account, brougbt him in not guilty; which thing not pleaſing the priſoners adverſaries, <hi>Joſeph Phipps</hi> was put by to be tryed by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Jury; and accordingly in the afternoon when he was to come to his Tryal (which was upon the third Account for Meeting) <hi>W. Armorer</hi> called to the Bailiffs, ſaying, go out and pick a Jury, there are honeſt men enough in the Town you, know. <hi>Tho: Skeats</hi> the Baliiff anſwered, yes Sir <hi>William,</hi> I'le fit you; upon which he went forth, and warning one <hi>Charles Belwood,</hi> formerly <hi>W. Armorers</hi> Man, he ſeemed very unwilling to come, which when <hi>W.</hi> A. under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, ſent for him again the ſecond time, threatning to fine him if he did not come (it may be, believing he would be a man fit for his purpoſe, for he hardly ever failed in any Jury, to bring in a <hi>Quaker</hi> guilty.) So a Jury being called, one of the priſoners <hi>Sarah Lamboll</hi> (wife of <hi>George Lamboll,</hi> who is one of the Premunired perſons) was called to the Barr, and they tendered the Oath of Allegiance to her again, and ſent her back to the Gaol.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Joſeph Phipps</hi> was called to the Barr, and his Indictment was read, to which he had pleaded not guilty the Seſſions before at <hi>Newberry:</hi> So he pleaded that there were not the number of five that was of age when he was taken at the Meeting. <hi>Edw: Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>by</hi> who
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:56124:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſate Judg, replyed, that was no matter, though there were but one of the age of ſixteen years, yet if there were five at the Meeting, he would ſend that one to priſon as a breaker of the Law: The Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner replyed, how can they make up the number, if they are not takeable?</p>
               <p>Judge, yes, they do make up the number, being perſons, though we cannot puniſh them by that Law; but we have another Law, by which we can fine them Twelve pence a piece for not going to Church.</p>
               <p>Ay, ſays <hi>W. Armo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er,</hi> there are the three Girls <hi>(Lydia Herſent, M. K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt</hi> and <hi>Sarah Kent)</hi> I ſent to priſon for not paying their Twelve pence a piece, and there they ſhall lye till they pay it; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther words were ſpoken to the ſame purpoſe, and ſo the Jury went forth, the Judg very much inſenſiing the Jury againſt the Priſoner, that they might bring him in guilty. And <hi>W. Armorer</hi> ſent the Clerk with them with the Act and Indictment, to inform the Jury: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome time, the Court ſent to know whether they were agreed? anſwer was returned, no: So <hi>W. Armorer</hi> ſent <hi>Rich: Grover</hi> his Clerk, who returned, ſaying, they are not agreed, and I think never will. And after a little ſpace, they ſent for the Jury, and asked if they were agreed? they anſwered no, the Court asked why? they anſwered, they were not ſatisfied as to the number of perſons, that were at the Meetings, and that there was nothing proved as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of exerciſe, and if there were the number, there was nothing proved what they did there: The Judg then called to <hi>R. Grover,</hi> who was the witneſs againſt the Priſoner, to know what he ſaid, who anſwered, That the Priſoner confeſſed that they were there to ſeek the Lord. Upon which the Judg doubled the words over again, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> look you there, he ſaid, they were there to ſeek the Lord: The Priſoner replyed, ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is it a crime worthy of Baniſhment to ſeek the Lord?</p>
               <p>The Judge <hi>Edw: Dolby,</hi> ſaid yes, (by which the Reader may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive what lodges in theſe mens hearts who would be called Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Magiſtrates.)</p>
               <p>Oh unheard of Cruelty! let the very Turks and Heathen be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed to hear of theſe things! and let the names of ſuch be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed in Infamy for ever, and let their memorial rot, who account a crime worthy of baniſhment or death, to confeſs the ſeeking of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:56124:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> God. Well, but not to digreſs, though it be hard to go over theſe things without continual admiration; but that we deſire not to be larger then a bare Relation of their unreaſonable proceedings, leaving it to the ingenuous Readers underſtanding for amplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</p>
               <p>So then, <hi>W. Armorer</hi> ſpoke ſomething to the Jury, and that he could never find our Friends in any exerciſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon which one of the Jury-men replyed, That he looked on it as an unequal thing that he ſhould be Witneſs and Judg too.</p>
               <p>At which <hi>W. Armorer</hi> began to be angry, and demanded what the Jury-man was, and would ſee his face, and bid him pull his Hat from his Noſe, and asked whether he did go to Church, and whether he was not one of them?</p>
               <p>Who anſwered, No, he was none of them, nor never was at any of their Meetings; and that he did go to Church.</p>
               <p>So the Jury being called over by their Names, the Court bid them divide, thoſe that would find the Priſoner guilty, from thoſe that could not, which were ſix of each.</p>
               <p>Upon which <hi>W. Armorer</hi> began to threaten thoſe that could not find the Priſoner guilty, and would have had them fined.</p>
               <p>The Judg ſaid, <hi>No, let them go together again, and it may be they may be better ſatisfied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the Jury went out the ſecond time, and after ſome time the Court ſent out to know whether they were agreed.</p>
               <p>Anſwer was returned, No.</p>
               <p>But the Court ſent in again, threatning the Jury that they would adjourn, and then would not accept of any private Verdict, but they ſhould be kept there all night without fire or candle.</p>
               <p>Which accordingly after a little ſpace was done, and the Court broke up, and order, was given that none ſhould come at the Jury, and that they ſhould not have fire nor candle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Jury being kept all night, and the Court being ſate the next morning, they ſent to the Jury to know if they were agreed.</p>
               <p>Who returned anſwer, No.</p>
               <p>But after ſome time, two of the Jury-men began to yeeld, it is judged rather through fear and wearineſs, then being ſatisfied in their judgments. And ſome of them cryed, A verdict, a verdict; and ſo they came in.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:56124:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> And the Court asked if they were agreed?</p>
               <p>One of them anſwered, He was not ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. Armorer</hi> replyed, <hi>You ſhall be ſatisfied;</hi> and the Fore-man ſaying <hi>Guilty,</hi> they took no farther notice, though four of them were not ſatisfied, but in haſt calling the Priſoner to the Barr, the Judg, <hi>Edw: D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lby,</hi> paſt ſentence on him, <hi>That he ſhould be tranſpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ted to ſome of His Majeſties Plantations, there to remain ſeven years.</hi> So was returned back to the Gaol. The Priſoner ſeeing of them reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do their work, ſaid little to them; but ſome ſhort time after, ſent a Letter to <hi>Edw: Dolby;</hi> a Copy whereof here followeth.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Reading-Gaol</hi> 
                           <date>the 23d of the 11th Month, 1666.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <salute>Juſtice Dolby,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>SEeing thou ſateſt as Judg of the Seſſions the laſt week, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt ſentence of Baniſhment againſt me, and being not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſpeak then for my ſelf in the Court, but threatned to be gag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, though my life was concerned; I now ſend this unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hee, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring thy ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ous conſideration hereof: And what hath been done againſt me, and how unjuſtly I have been proceeded againſt from firſt to laſt, till ſentence of Exilement from my Native Countrey be paſt, I leave to the witneſs of God in thy own Conſcience, which can bring thy actions to thy remembrance, and will ſpeak the truth of all things as they are: To which I do refer thee for a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular account of all things that have paſt; and with which I leave my cauſe to be pleaded even in thy own conſcience, between the Lord and thee; only hereby I give a hint of ſome things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thou mayeſt remember, that when <hi>W. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>morer</hi> and thy ſelf came to the houſe of <hi>Thomas Curtis,</hi> I was there with two perſons more above the age of ſixteen years, beſides <hi>A. Curtis,</hi> and ſome children, who are not to be accounted as perſons to make up the number five: And it appears by the Act, that four may meet; and alſo W. A. and ſeveral others of the Kings Juſtices, have told us that four may meet, and they would not meddle with us; and it is ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to think that children of twelve or fourteen years of age will
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56124:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> plot or contrive inſurrections; for againſt ſuch perſons as do ſo contrive inſurrections, and plot againſt the Government, the Act was intended, according to the Preamble of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And beſides, if ſuch childrens being there, do make up the number, how is it that you puniſh not the children by that Law? And if the children are not under the breach of that Law, how can three perſons break it, there being no more there? I leave to thy conſideration. And the Witneſs did only ſay we were there to ſeek the Lord, (or that we ſaid ſo) now I hope the Act will not (ſimply in it ſelf) take hold of ſuch as meet together to ſeek the Lord, for that is according to the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which ſaith, <hi>That in all places, and at all times, men ought to perform holy duty to God;</hi> and no other could be proved againſt me, but that we ſaid we were there to ſeek the Lord; and is it not a ſad thing that men ſhould ſo far loſe their reaſon and moderation, and deny Chriſtianity, as to baniſh people for meeting together to ſeek the Lord, and to perform holy duty to him, when nothing elſe can be proved, except they will make it a crime worthy of Baniſhment and Death, to be at the Houſe of <hi>Tho: Curtis,</hi> which no Law doth; for no man can prove, nor ever ſhall find, that we meet to contrive Inſurrections, or plot againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and the God of Heaven knows, (who knows the intents of the hearts of all men) that we never ſo much as thought, much leſs intended any ſuch thing; and thy own conſcience may tell thee the ſame. And this not being proved, how can any impartial Jury find us guilty of the breach of this Act, and bring us in guilty of Baniſhment, (and Death if we return) when nothing can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved but that we were at ſuch a place, and ſaid we were ſeeking the Lord? For nothing elſe did ever appear: And yet notwithſtanding the Jury muſt go on right or wrong, or elſe be threatned with fines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in caſe they bring in not guilty, when they are upon their oaths, and ought to go according to the Evidence, and not to put their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to the vote, and to give away the Liberties, Lives, Rights and Priviledges of free-born <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, and to oppreſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Kings Subjects, by violating his Laws, and turning of them to a wrong end, as in this caſe. This Act was made againſt ſuch as do at their Meetings contrive inſurrections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not againſt ſuch as do meet really to ſeek the Lord, as appears by the Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it: Therefore ſuch as do puniſh people for ſeeking the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56124:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> Lord, do go quite contrary to the Act, and turns it to a wrong end, and are no true Friends to the King in ſo doing, though they pretend Law, and to act according to Law, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed their own wills and malicious minds, leads them contrary to Laws; and how contrary it was to the Conſciences of ſome of the Jury-man, thou mighteſt ſee, who were not ſatisfied, no nor (it is believed, and credibly reported) are not to this day, but is a load upon their Conſciences, and may well be, in that they gave away their power, and indeed the power of the Law, being over-awed by high words; for they ought to have been ſat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sfied in their own Conſciences, and not to have looked at the diſpleaſure of any man, being ſworn well and truly to try, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which I doubt not but thou very well knoweſt, if thou hadſt but done accordingly; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe things be according to Reaſon and Equity, upon which the ancient Laws are ſaid to be grounded, I ſay, I ſhall leave to the Witneſs of God in thy Conſcience, which anſwers the righteous Law, and which will deal truly and plainly with thee, and will either condemn or juſtifie thee in the day of Account. For Friend, know this, and mind alſo in ſecret, That an account to God the Judg of quick and dead, muſt be given by thee, and all men upon the earth; and aſſuredly he doth behold and mark thy actions, and they are record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Book of remembrance, which ſhall be accounted for; and though thou maiſt hide thy ſelf as from man, yet thou canſt not hide thy ſelf from him who is the ſearcher of all hearts, and the tryer of all reins; who will proceed in judgment according to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Equity, by the impartial Evidence of his Witneſs, the Light of Jeſus Chriſt in thy Conſcience, which will bring all thy ways and doings to remembrance, and lay thee open and naked before the Lord God. And Friend, to receive the ſentence of condemnation, and to be baniſhed for ever from his preſence will be a very ſad ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and far worſe then to be baniſhed from the Land of ones Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, into a ſtrange and Foreign Countrey, for the exerciſe of ones Conſcience towards God, in meeting to ſeek and wait upon him, and to have and enjoy his preſence with one; yet ſuch as do ſo baniſh, do very badly in ſo doing, and which God will undoubtedly call them to a ſtrict account for. And in this is my comfort, that though thou haſt ſentenced me to Baniſhment, yet thou canſt not baniſh me from the Lords preſence, nor deprive me of the peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:56124:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> which is received through Faith, and living-obedience to the will and requirings of God, and becauſe it is not for evil-doing, for curſing, ſwearing, drunkenneſs, blaſpheming the Name of God, hurting or wronging any man in this place in which I was born and brought up, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but only becauſe I was met with two or three more to ſeek God. Oh! may you not be aſhamed to profeſs the Name of God and Chriſt, and baniſh thoſe that meet in his Name? and profeſs Chriſtianity, and yet baniſh it out of your coaſts. And if Chriſt were now here among you, as he was among the cruel Jews, would you not baniſh him if he met with his Diſciples? who met upon Mountains by the Sea-ſide, and other places, ſeparate from the Jews and Heathens Synagogues and Temples, which he and his Apoſtles gathered people from, to worſhip God in the ſpirit and truth, and brought them to know their bodies to be the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt. I ſay, if he were here now, and did meet, would you not baniſh him, as you do his followers? And in as much as you do it unto them, you do it unto him, againſt whom ye are ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, who will be too hard for you; for never did any ſtrive againſt the Lord, and proſper.</p>
                     <p>And that thou ſhouldſt be found in this work beyond moſt in the Nation, will be no credit to thee; and truly this action has far out-ſtript the cruel Jews, who though their Law allowed forty ſtripes, yet would the Executioners give but thirty nine, becauſe they would not deal with perſons to the rigor of the Law, which you have cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly gone beyond; and exceeded upon me. And as the Lord God doth mark thy actions, ſo will men alſo mark thee, and take notice of thy doings.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore it would be well to conſider and repent of what thou haſt done, and not raſhly to run (nor to be led) on in this work of perſecuting of innocent people for the exerciſe of their tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences towards God, conſidering the reward that hath attended Perſecutors in all ages, and how their Names have been a reproach and a ſtink in after-generations; and will not ſuch much more ſtink, that ſentence people to Baniſhment for ſeeking the Lord, and put I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons upon them, and then link two of us together in Irons as if we were ſuch intollerable offenders, as were not worthy to live. For as ſoon (almoſt) as I came in, Irons were clapt on me, and then link<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Chriſtopher Cheeſeman,</hi> who had Irons alſo; but through Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56124:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                        <hi>Armorers</hi> means (as I am informed) the Irons were taken off again, and only the Locks remains on our Legs, which I doubt not but thou mighteſt cauſe to be taken off, if thou wouldſt: However I am well contented, knowing I have not deſerved this cruel uſage at the Gaolers hands, nor at thine; but this cruelty and the bitterneſs of Envy, is hereby in ſome meaſure made manifeſt.</p>
                     <p>But I ſhall forbear to lay o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en the Gaolers cruelty, it being not pertinent to my preſent buſineſs, and rather deſire thou mayeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of the things before mentioned, ſo as to amend thy ways and doings, whereby thou mayeſt free thy ſelf from that guilt, which no man can acquit thee of, which thou wilt attract by theſe unneigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-like, unchriſtian-like, yea, and I may ſay, unlaw-like Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
                     <p>I remain a lover of thy ſoul, a witneſs againſt injuſtice and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, in the long-ſuffering ſpirit of Jeſus, for whoſe ſake thou haſt given ſentence of BANISHMENT againſt me from the Land of my Nativity, who have learned to do good to them that hate and perſecute me, who am called</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Joſeph Phipps.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The <hi>27th</hi> of the <hi>11th</hi> Month called <hi>January,</hi> 1666, <hi>W. Armorer</hi> came early to the Meeting again; and there being but four young Maidens, <hi>viz. Hannah Kent, Sarah Binfield, Eliz: Whiteheart,</hi> and <hi>Anne</hi> her Siſter: He ſaid, <hi>Here is a goodly company:</hi> and commanded one of his men to fetch ſome water: His man went to <hi>Dan: Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> and borrowed a Bucket and a naſty Bowl-diſh, and having brought the Bucket of water into the Meeting-room, <hi>W. Armorer</hi> took the Bowl-diſh, and filling it with the water, threw it with great violence in the Maidens faces, filling the diſh many times ſo faſt one after another, that with the violent throwing in their faces, and the coldneſs of the water, one of the Maidens was like to loſe her breath, and ſate down, being wet in ſuch a cruel inhumane manner, that it run down their necks, and wet them very much, ſo that they were fain to go bome and change their clothes, it being in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time. And having turned them out of the Meeting-room, he went his ways.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:56124:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> And how unlike a Juſtice this was, let the Reader judg, but more like a rude ſavage creature, indeed hardly like a man, and yet this is the man that rules as King in the Town of <hi>Reading,</hi> that doth what he will without controle. Well, again</p>
               <p>The <hi>17th</hi> of the firſt Month called <hi>March,</hi> 1667, <hi>W. Armorer</hi> and <hi>Tho. Coats,</hi> Mayor, came to the Meeting, and took <hi>Henry Adams, Sarah Binfield, Eliz: Whitebeart, Mary Webb,</hi> and <hi>Eliz: Tudway</hi> the younger, and ſent them all to the Houſe of Correction, though there were but four of the age of ſixteen years, <hi>H. Adams</hi> on the third account, <hi>Eliz: Whiteheart</hi> and <hi>Mary Webb</hi> for ſix Months, <hi>S. Binfield</hi> for three Months, and <hi>Eliz: Tudway,</hi> being not fourteen years of age, till ſhe paid Twelve pence for not being at his Church.</p>
               <p>A day or two after, a Neighbour of <hi>Eliz: Tudways</hi> (the woman having a love to the child) went to <hi>W. Armorer,</hi> and offered to pay the twelve pence; notwithſtanding <hi>W. Armorer</hi> refuſed, and told her, That except ſhe would pay twelve pence more, ſhe ſhould not be diſcharged, though ſhe was committed but for one twelve pence.</p>
               <p>But the woman refuſing to pay the other twelve pence to his Clerk, <hi>Richard Grover,</hi> the child remains in priſon to this day, her Father and Mother being both Priſoners alſo at the County-Gaol, having three ſmall ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ldren beſides.</p>
               <p>And having ſent the five above named to priſon, they <hi>(W. Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> and <hi>Tho: Coats)</hi> went into the houſe of <hi>Tho: Curtis,</hi> and going up ſtairs, went into A. <hi>Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tis</hi> her Chamber, where ſhe was not being very well. <hi>W. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rmorer</hi> proteſted he would ſend her to Gaol becauſe the Meeting was cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nued at the houſe; but if ſhe would ſhut up the doors, and ſuffer no more Meetings, ſhe ſhould have her Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Curtis</hi> replyed, the houſe was her Husbands, aad he might do what he would with it; and bid them judg whether they themſelves would look on it as an equal thing for their Wives to contradict their ſervants in w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at they did require them to do.</p>
               <p>And after ſome other diſcourſe of this and other things, being going away, <hi>W. Armo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> bid A. C. make her ready, proteſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g he would ſend her to Gaol: And accordingly ſent up the Conſtable, <hi>Jo: Stretch,</hi> to her Chamber, to have her to the Gaol, ſaying, That
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:56124:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> Sir <hi>William</hi> had ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. To whom ſhe anſwered, That ſhe was not then in a capacity to go. So the Conſtable civilly went away.</p>
               <p>But the next day W. A ſent him again, being very angry, and threatned if he did not carry her to Gaol, he would lay him by the heels.</p>
               <p>So the Conſtable came to her again, having a Warrant authorizing him to take the body of A. <hi>Curtis,</hi> and have her to the Gaol, to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ept upon her former Commitment, from which ſhe was freed, as appears by the diſcharge under his own hand before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, of which the Reader may take notice. So ſhe was had to the Gaol, where ſhe now remains.</p>
               <p>The <hi>16th</hi> of the ſecond Month, called <hi>April,</hi> 1667, the Seſſions was holden at <hi>Newberry</hi> for the County; to which place <hi>Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> was had, being committed on the third account for meeting. And heing called to the Barr, an Indictment was read againſt him for being at an unlawful Seditious Meeting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which he pleaded Not guilty of any Seditious Meeting, or plotting, or contriving Inſurrections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the Court asked the Priſoner if he would give bond to appear the next Seſſions.</p>
               <p>He anſwered, He was a ſtranger in that place; but if they would take his word to appear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he would promiſe to appear.</p>
               <p>But being not accepted, the Gaoler took him away, and had him back again to the Gaol.</p>
               <p>The Priſoner being returned, his Father, <hi>Henry Adams,</hi> living in the Town, and hearing that the Court had offered him liberty till the next Seſſions, upon bond of appearance, went himſelf to <hi>W Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morer,</hi> and offered to be bound for his Sons appearance. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it had been proffered, W. A. would not take it, but began to rail againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and telling ſuch ſtories concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are incredible to any man of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>The <hi>9th</hi> of the <hi>4th</hi> Month, called <hi>June,—</hi>67, W. A. came again to the Meeting, and pull'd out the Friends there met, and ſo let them go; which was not uſual to let any go out of his hands after he had taken them.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>14th</hi> of the <hi>5th</hi> Month, called <hi>July,—</hi>67, W. A. his man came to the Meeting, and having looked in, went out at the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:56124:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> door, and pulled the door after him; it being a Spring-lock, catcht, and ſhut himſelf out.</p>
               <p>Soon after came <hi>W. Armorer,</hi> and finding the door ſhut, ſent for a Sledg to break it open; but one of the Friends perceiving that he would break open the door, went and opened it, ſaying, <hi>I do open the door, that that thou mayeſt ſee our innoc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncy, that we are not plotting againſt the Government; for if we were</hi> (as he has often accuſed us) <hi>we would not have opened the door.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He replyed, If you had not, I would have broken it open, though his own man lockt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Daniel Seamer</hi> (one of the Neighbours) coming into the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-room with them, ſaid, Sir <hi>William, I hope the next Rejoycing-day, all theſe forms and ſtools ſhall be brought out to help make a Bonfire.</hi> To which <hi>W. Armorer</hi> willingly aſſented.</p>
               <p>So <hi>R. Grover</hi> his Clerk took the Names of nine, viz. <hi>Rich: Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins, John Litleworth, Anne Sharp, Eliz: Tudway, Mary Coale, Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah Kent, Martha Cheeſeman, Francis Greenaway,</hi> and <hi>Eliz: Booth;</hi> and being had to his houſe, where was alſo <hi>Edw: Dolby,</hi> they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted five to the Houſe of Correction for three Months, <hi>Martha Cheeſeman</hi> being one, whoſe Husband is a Priſoner at the Gaol; by which he ſhews his deſtructive ſpirit to humane ſociety. And in ſome diſcourſe <hi>Eliz: Tudway,</hi> one of the Priſoners, telling <hi>W. A.</hi> that theſe things muſt be accounted for one day: He anſwered, <hi>Aye, you ſhall ſee at the Day of Judgment, whoſe arſe will be blackeſt, yours or mine.</hi> And ſuch like communication he has many times, which is almoſt a ſhame for Civility to mention, but that people may ſee what a man this is to make a Juſtice.</p>
               <p>And going to another, <hi>Eliz: Booth,</hi> ſtripped up her ſleeve, ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her if ſhe had any black ſtrings about her arm: She anſwered, No, ſhe was no Papiſt. But (ſaid he) you are bewitched.</p>
               <p>So a Mittimus being made, they ſent <hi>Mary Coale</hi> to Gaol for ſix Months, (her Husband <hi>Leo: Coale,</hi> being there a Premunired-perſon, and two of his Brothers) and A. <hi>Sharp, Eliz: Tudway,</hi> and <hi>Hannah Kent,</hi> to the Gaol on the third account.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>16th</hi> of the ſame Month, the Seſſions was holden at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingdon,</hi> to which place <hi>H. Adams,</hi> A <hi>Sharp, E. Tudway,</hi> and <hi>H. Kent</hi> were had; and the ſame day the three women were called to the Bar, and an Indictment being read againſt them for being at an unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:56124:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> Meeting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they pleaded Not guilty. So the Court told them, That if they would give Security for their appearance the next Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, they might have their liberty. Upon which a Neighbour of <hi>E. Tudway</hi>'s, <hi>Tho: Skeats,</hi> proffered to be bound for her. And another man ſtanding by, ſaid he would be bound for her, though he never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw her face before. But the Clerk of the Seſſions, <hi>Geo: Champion,</hi> hearing that, ſaid, They might do that at <hi>Reading,</hi> and they would leave it to Sir W. A. and Juſtice <hi>Dolby:</hi> So they were taken from the Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, and after they came to <hi>Reading,</hi> there was a very ſufficient man of the Town, <hi>Jo: Kent,</hi> went to W. A. and proffered to be bound for his daughter <hi>Hannah</hi> her appearance the next Seſſions, but he would not take it.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>H. Adams</hi> was called to the Barr, and W. A. and the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces called for a Jury, picking ſuch and ſuch men; naming them, the Judg, <hi>Tho: Holt,</hi> ſaying, Put down ſuch a man, he is an honeſt man. The Jury being ſworn well and truly to try, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Indictment was read, to which the Priſoner had pleaded Not guilty the Seſſions before at <hi>Newberry.</hi> So now he deſired that Witneſs might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to prove what the Fact was, or the evil he had done; and if he had done any evil, was willing to ſuffer accordingly. But no witneſs appearing to prove any thing that he had done, neither that he was at any Meeting, the Judg called for the Records; upon which the Clerk made diligent ſearch, and ſent his man out of the Court to look after them, and his man returned with great Rolls of Paper under his Arms, but could not find the Records. Then the Judg ſtood up, ſaying, <hi>If you have loſt the Rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ds for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> firſt and ſecond of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, we can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ceed, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>his mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> go for the firſt offence.</hi> Upon which W. A. ſtood up in great fury, ſaying he would take his Oath that the Records were true, though th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y were loſt. So they gave him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Book, and he kiſſed it, and ſate down again on the Bench as one of the Priſoners Judges.</p>
               <p>Then the Judg <hi>Tho: Holt</hi> turned his tale again, like himſelf, and many others ſuch as he is, who can turn ſometimes one way, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times another, ſaid, <hi>You Gentlemen of the Jury, you ſee here is</hi> Sir W. A. <hi>hath t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Oath,</hi> (having only taken the Book in his hand, and kiſſed it) <hi>That the Records are true, though they are loſt; and you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude there was a firſt and ſecond offence, before there can be a third</hi> (though there was no witneſs to prove a third offence, but becauſe W. A. had
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:56124:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> kiſſed the Book, and ſaid the Records were true, though they were loſt, for the firſt and ſecond; therefore they would conclude too, that this was the third) and ſaid the Judg, <hi>You cannot but find him guilty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the Jury went forth, and in a little time returned, and their Verdict was, <hi>Not guilty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the Judg ſtood up, ſaying, <hi>How ſo? hath not Sir</hi> W. Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer <hi>ſworn that the Records are true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after the Jury had given ſome reaſons why they could not find him guilty, they went forth the ſecond time, and a Bailif was ſworn to lock them up, and that none ſhould come at them. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, ſoon after they were gone out, W. A. went off the Bench to the Jury, and threatned them, as ſome of themſelves did ſince confeſs; and a little after W. A.'s return to the Court, the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry came in, and the Fore-man ſaid the Priſoner was found guilty: But ſome of the Jury not being ſatisfied, would not come into the Court, for they did not agree to the Verdict; and one of them ſaid he never would agree to it: And being in a confuſion, being much threatned, they would not appear; but the Court being in a hurry, and angry, the Judg ſaid they ſhould be fined if they did not come in: Upon which (being over-awed by high words and threatnings) they came in; and being called over, they called the Priſoner to the Barr, and asked him what he had to ſay for himſelf? The Priſoner ſaid, <hi>Was there not a Bailif ſworn that none ſhould come at the Jury, but they ſhould be locked up, &amp;c. and which of you have made this man for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear himſelf? was it not thee?</hi> pointing to W. A. At which they laughed, ſaying it was by the leave of the Court. The Priſoner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, <hi>Well, I ſee you have a cunning way to ſwear, and your wills are your Law; and 'tis to littl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> purpoſe what I ſay to you, for you are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined what to do; and if I muſt be a ſufferer for well-doing, the will of the Lord be done.</hi> (For nothing of evil could be proved, no not ſo much as the third offence, neither Records for the firſt and ſecond, as is ſaid.)</p>
               <p>Much more was ſpoken, but this in ſhort was the ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>So the Gaoler took him away, but no ſentence was given againſt him, and ſo he was returned to the Gaol where he now remains. And having ſince asked the Gaoler what order he had from the Court concerning him, telling him that he had no ſentence, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:56124:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> in Priſon. The Gaoler anſwered, <hi>Harry, thee art for Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſportation, they have done it ſince among themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now whether theſe things be accord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng to the Law, according to which theſe men pretend they proceed, let all that have any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg therein judg; but we are ſure it is not according to Reaſon and Equity, upon which the Laws ought to be grounded: And if theſe proceedings be not according to Law, how can theſe men bring honor to the King and his Government, by theſe things? Let the wiſe in heart judg; and the Lord give men underſtanding and hearts to look into theſe things, leſt the pretence of Law and Legal Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, become a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nare and a Ginne unto the Innocent and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</p>
               <p>And this is as ſhort Account of the Proceedings of <hi>W. Armorer,</hi> as we could draw up, to keep the ſubſtance. Many circumſtances we have omitted, for we deſire not to wade in ſuch things, but rather to ſpeak the leaſt of things, then to go one jot beyond. But much more we could ſay; and theſe things our very Adverſaries them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may remember, if they will but call to mind their actions. And though the ſaid <hi>W. Armorer</hi> hath dealt thus hardly with us, to throw us into priſon heaps upon heaps, we may ſay; yet his enmity againſt us is farther made manifeſt, in that he hath many times charged the Gaoler not to ſuffer one of us to go over the threſhold, but to keep us in very cloſe, both in the extream heat of Summer, when many thouſands have dyed through Infectious and Peſtilential Diſeaſes, and ſeveral in this Town; even then have we been thronged toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as if it were on purpoſe to deſtroy us: And alſo in the very cold Winters, three of which we have patiently endured, and now almoſt four Summers; and if any ſhould ask the reaſon, why the fore-going Relation may anſwer for us, which will tell them, 'Tis for ſeeking the Lord, for waiting upon him, for worſhipping him, for making conſcience of our wayes, and becauſe we cannot tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs his righteous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw and Commandment, who faith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for any evil-doing: For if out adverſaries t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emſelves had a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y evil to lay to our cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no doubt they would publiſh it to the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ole world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and we deſire they may. And yet though we have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> us hardly uſed, yet bleſſed be the Lord we are yet alive, thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our health may be much impaired, or ſome of us at leaſt; and but one hath dyed in priſon, and one not long after he was releaſed,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:56124:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> which was judged his Impriſonment might be a great cauſe of, being kept in, in very cold weather, and taking great cold; and when we have been ſick, and have deſired to go out to take things neceſſary, which could not well be done in the priſon, where ſo many Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are, it has been denyed, and we muſt not be ſuffered, though our lives ſometimes have been concerned, except we would give ſuch Bonds and Engagements, which it is not unlikely but he himſelf knew we could not for Conſcience-ſake do, and only to be at a houſe in the ſame Town. And <hi>A: Gurtis</hi> being not well a little time ſince, the Gaoler ſent to him to know if ſhe might go home to her houſe, it being extream hot weather, and having but little room in the Gaol, he would not permit her: And a Friend being with him afterward, and telling him how they were thronged up together, and how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream hot it was in the Gaol, the Gaoler being preſent, ſaid, <hi>Sir</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam <hi>will let any of you out, giving ſecurity.</hi> He anſwered, <hi>No, Mrs.</hi> Curt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>ſhould not if ſhe would give ſecurity, but ſhould l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e there till ſhe rot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And alſo <hi>Chriſtopher Cheeſeman,</hi> another of the Priſoners, being very ſick, almo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> unto death, his wife went to <hi>W. A.</hi> with a Letter, to deſire liberty for him to go to his own houſe, being almoſt over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Gaol, to take things neceſſary for the recovery of his health, being kept in a cold Garret among many Priſoners, in the cold Winter-time; but <hi>W A.</hi> not only refuſed to grant the womans reaſonable deſire, but refuſed to take the Letter alſo, ſaying he ſhould lye there till he rot, before he would do it.</p>
               <p>So that he doth not only throng them up in Priſons, but makes himſelf as aoler alſo; ſo that though the Gaoler know his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an truſt them, as being true and faithful to their words; yet he muſt not let a Priſoner ſtir over the threſhold, for fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of diſpleaſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir <hi>William:</hi> Which dealing can hardly be parallel'd in <hi>England,</hi> that Juſtices ſhould be ſeekers after men without any complaint, Accuſers, Judges and Gaolers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now it may not be amiſs to give a ſhort Relation of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of <hi>Humph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ey Hide,</hi> a Juſtice ſo called, n the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounty, againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fome of our Friends, being h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Neighbours and Tenants, it being one in quality with <hi>W. Armorer</hi>'s, though not in quantity.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:56124:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>William Mathews, John Langly, Mary Slade</hi> Widow, and <hi>Richard Slade</hi> her Son, being ſummoned to appear at <hi>Abingdon</hi> at the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Quarter-Seſſions, hold en the <hi>14th</hi> day of the <hi>5th</hi> Month called <hi>July,</hi> 1663: At which place accordingly (having done no man wrong) they did appear, and being called to the Barr, and called by Name, an Indictment was read againſt them for not being at their Church in four Months before; and the Court asked them if they would conform and come to Church, or no? The Friends anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, They could not come to their Church, becauſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had never enjoyed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſence of God there, and that was the cauſe of their abſenting. Upon which the Court preſently began to proceed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any delay, or time of conſideration) to fine them according to the Law which was made for the paying of twelve pence for every firſt dayes abſence from their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hurch. But one of them began to queſt on whether that Law would hold them. A Lawyer ſtanding by, took up a Statute-Book, and found a Statute which was made for the Papiſts, to fine them twenty pounds a month, and ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> would hold them, he was ſure of it; ſo they read the Statu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to them, and fined them twenty pounds a month for the four months, which was eighty pounds a piece. But <hi>Humph: Hide</hi> who ſate Judg. pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ended he was ſorry for <hi>Rich Slade,</hi> and <hi>W. Mathews,</hi> ſaying they were good Harveſt-men, (for they deſired, that if any there had any evil to accuſe them of, they ſhould ſpeak) and <hi>H. Hide</hi> ſaid, he did believe that neither of them were able to pay the Fine: Which did the more manifeſt his hard-hearted Cruelty towards them, becauſe he knew they were not able to pay ſuch a great fine, which he, with the reſt, had impoſed upon them, being his Tenants, their Lives be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſome of his Eſtate, viz. <hi>Mary Slade,</hi> Widow, an ancient wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of near ſeventy years of age, and not a tooth in her head, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Tenant in poſſeſſion, and <hi>Richard</hi> her Son in reverſion, after her; and <hi>William Mathew</hi> in reverſion, and <hi>John Langly</hi> a Tenants Son, being all his Neighbours, and labouring-men, and having little but what they work for, being always his Neighbours. And ſome time after they were committed to the Gaol, <hi>William Mathew</hi> his Mother-in-law went to their Landlord, <hi>Humph: Hide,</hi> to ſee if ſhe could prevail with him to get <hi>William</hi>'s Liberty. He anſwered, He could not do any thing in it. She asked if he would give his conſent to his coming home. He anſwered, No, never while he did live; for
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:56124:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> he did not love them ſo well: And ſo they have remained Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers above theſe four years.</p>
               <p>Alſo another poor man and his wife, the one about 74 years, and the other near thereabouts, becauſe they could not go to their Worſhip, the woman being almoſt blind, the Conſtable going to their Houſe to diſtrain, and finding no goods, made a complaint to <hi>Humph: Hide,</hi> who cauſed the old man and his wife to be brought before him, and made a Mittimus, and ſent them to the Gaol, being above twenty miles from their habitation, becauſe they did not go to their Worſhip, to which he would force and compel them, or elſe the Gaol muſt be their habitation. The old mans Name was <hi>John Cooke,</hi> and <hi>Jane</hi> his Wife.</p>
               <p>The firſt day of the <hi>5th</hi> Month called <hi>July,—</hi>66, <hi>Humph: Hide</hi> ſent a party of Soldiers with a Corporal, and Capt. <hi>Garret</hi> with a party of Horſe and Foot, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſe of <hi>Bartholomew Mallam,</hi> in <hi>Lamburn</hi> Woodlands, and meeting with ſome Friends in the fields, they took them, and had them to the Hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and put them in at door, and then accuſed them for being at a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeting, and ſo took them, and had them down to <hi>Lamburn</hi> Town; to which place <hi>H. Hide,</hi> with ſome other Juſtices, were gathered; and being brought before them, they commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted <hi>Richa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>kes, Oliver Sanſome,</hi> and one more, to the Gaol for three months, and ſeven men more, to the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ewell</hi> at <hi>Abingdon</hi> for three months; and <hi>Barthol. Mallam,</hi> the man of the houſe, they committed upon the Statute of the 35 of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to the Gaol.</p>
               <p>And about the 4<hi>th</hi> of the <hi>8th</hi> Month, called <hi>October,—</hi>66, the Seſſions was holden a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Newberry,</hi> to which place <hi>B. M.</hi> was had, and indicted for being at a Meeting: To which having pleaded Not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they demanded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eties till next Seſſions, upon which two of his acquai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ged for his appearance, and ſo he had his liberty til next Seſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>And t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ext Seſſions being holden at <hi>Reading</hi> the <hi>16th</hi> day of the <hi>11th</hi> Month cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed <hi>January,—</hi>66, he had his Tryal, and the Jury brought him in Not guilty of the breach of that Statute, but guilty of not coming to their Church, becauſe the Conſtable ſwore againſt him that he had not ſeen him at their Church in two years; ſo he was fined.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Reading</hi> 
                  <date>the <hi>15th</hi> of the <hi>6th</hi> Month, 1667.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_prisoners">
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:56124:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Remains PRISONERS in the Gaol, Forty.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Twenty one having the Sentence of a Premunire paſt againſt them.</item>
               <item>Three for refuſing the Oath of Allegiance.</item>
               <item>Five under the Sentence of BANISHMENT.</item>
               <item>Three fined twelve-pence a piece, being under the age of ſixteen years, taken at a Meeting.</item>
               <item>Four for being at meeting, three on the third account, one for ſix months.</item>
               <item>Four fined eighty pounds a piece, for not going to Steeple-houſe.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Priſoners remaining at the Houſe of Correction, Eight.</head>
               <item>Five committed for three months, for meeting.</item>
               <item>Two for ſix months.</item>
               <item>One Child fined twelve-pence for not being at Steeple-houſe, being taken at a Meeting.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
